<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Common-prayer-book devotions, episcopal delusions, or, The Second death of the service-book wherein the unlawfulness (with advantage) of the imposition of liturgies ... is clearly and plainly demonstrated from the Scriptures ...</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1666</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 211 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 40 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A34136</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C5572</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R35602</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">15491108</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 15491108</idno>
            <idno type="VID">103564</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A34136)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 103564)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1186:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Common-prayer-book devotions, episcopal delusions, or, The Second death of the service-book wherein the unlawfulness (with advantage) of the imposition of liturgies ... is clearly and plainly demonstrated from the Scriptures ...</title>
                  <author>C. W.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[7], 70 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1666.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"To the reader" signed: C.W.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England. --  Book of common prayer --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Corinne Vieracker</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Corinne Vieracker</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="note">
            <pb facs="tcp:103564:1"/>
            <head>Note,</head>
            <p>THIS Diſcourſe was drawn up during the Regency and Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Old <hi>Service-Book,</hi> ſince which time, the many Diſeaſes cleaving to it, have (it ſeems) occaſioned the Death of it: and this, the raiſing up of another in its ſtead, of a new Calculation: So that, I know not whether the Scrutinie here made into the former Book, will in all Points touch with the latter: I ſuppoſe the Herings in the one Barrel, differ not much from thoſe in the other.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:103564:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Common-Prayer-Book DEVOTIONS, Epiſcopal Deluſions; OR, THE <hi>SECOND DEATH</hi> OF The Service-Book.</p>
            <p>WHEREIN, The unlawfulneſs (with advantage) of the Impoſition of Liturgies, or ſtinted Forms of Prayer, or of the Worſhip of God (and more eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of the <hi>Engliſh Service-Book</hi>) is clearly and plainly demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated from the Scriptures, and grounds in Reaſon; with Anſwers to the Arguments and Pleas inſiſted on, in Defence of the ſaid Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions.</p>
            <q>
               <p>But they ſhall proceed no further: for their folly ſhall be manifeſt unto all men, as theirs alſo was,
<bibl>
                     <hi>2 Tim. 3.9.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
               <p>His Spirit was ſtirred within him, when he ſaw the City wholly given to Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry.
<bibl>
                     <hi>Acts 17.16.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
               <p>For this cauſe was I born, and for this cauſe came I into the world, that I ſhould bear witneſs unto the Truth,
<bibl>
                     <hi>John, 18.37.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
               <p>— And ſo will I go in unto the King, which is not according to the Law: and if I periſh, I periſh;
<bibl>
                     <hi>Heſter 4.16.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
               <p>Am I therefore become your enemy, becauſe I tell you the truth?
<bibl>
                     <hi>Gal. 4.16.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
               <p>Adulterum eſt, impium eſt, ſacrilegium eſt, quicquid humano furore inſtituitur, ut diſpoſitio divina violetur.
<bibl>
                     <hi>Cypr. Lib. 1. Ep. 8.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
               <p>Veritati poteſt nemo preſcribere, non ſpacium temporum, no patrocinia perſonarum.
<bibl>
                     <hi>Teitul. de Veland. Virg.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
               <p>Doctis, &amp; in ſpeciem ſanctis, hoc conſuetum, ut caeteris Chriſto obnixius reſiſtant.
<bibl>
                     <hi>Mulculus</hi> in <hi>Mat. p. 423.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the Year, 1666.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:103564:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:103564:2"/>
            <head>To the Conſcientious Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>CHRISTIAN READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THIS enſuing Diſcourſe needeth no E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle to commend it, nor humane Patron to protect it, an Epiſtolary Porch can add no more to its worth, than a well placed Beauty-Spot to a good Complection, whoſe Brightneſs is ſet off by the contrary Blackneſs; The Workman was a perſon as well furniſhed with Stuff, Tools &amp; Skill for Temple-work, as moſt this laſt learned Age hath produced, &amp; the weighty Truth he ſo ſtrenuouſly preſſeth in this enſuing Tract, was not the exerciſe of his Skill and Parts, but the genuine birth of his Heart and Conſcience; a Truth ſo dear to him, that he choſe rather to part with Liberty, Livelyhood, and dear Relations, than to ſhake hands and bid farewel to ſo endeared a Companion: a Truth for which he had been a Sufferer in former Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions, and for adhering to which, he ended his dayes in a kind of Exile, in this preſent Storm; a Truth that was ſo revived upon his Heart, and ſo powerfully preſt upon his Conſcience, when the Bloſſoms of the Grave were upon him, and the welcome meſſengers of Death had ſummon'd him to his Reſt, that he could not Dye till he had Commended it, nay, Commanded it to all that fear the Lord. The ſubject matter being a Defence of Pure Primitive Worſhip, needs no
<pb facs="tcp:103564:3"/>Patron but he that is our Lord and Law-giver, who ſtands with his Sword drawn to beat off all Copemates in this his Prerogative, and although <hi>FILII PERDITIONIS</hi> may tug hard to juſtle Jeſus Chriſt out of his Throne, and to ſit Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount in the Temple of God, chopping and changing Divine Inſtitutions for Humane Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, yet the day is at hand, when the Builder of the Goſpel-Temple, ſhall plead his right with fury poured out: How light ſoever ſome <hi>Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, Latitudinarians,</hi> and others, <hi>homines omnium hora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> may ſet by Inſtituted Worſhip, yet in all Ages of the World, the ſincere Servants of God have choſen rather Baniſhment and Death, than to embrace the Cuſtoms of the Heathens, or the Inſtitutes of <hi>Roman Babylon</hi> in their <hi>Divine Service,</hi> as both the Scriptures and Eccleſiaſtical Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters fully demonſtrate. Come we to our late times, even ſince the Witneſſes in the <hi>Marian days;</hi> Where were more Learned, more Godly Men in the World, than <hi>Cartwright, Parker, Reynolds, Green<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, Ames?</hi> and who knoweth not that theſe and many more of the ſame heavenly ſtamp, ſuffered extream Perſecution, Deprivations and Baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, rather than they would touch with the <hi>Graven Images, the work of the Craftsmen,</hi> that <hi>then were,</hi> and <hi>now are,</hi> the Snares and Nets upon <hi>Miſpah</hi> and <hi>Tabor?</hi> Holy <hi>Cotton, Shepherd,</hi> and many others, emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent for Piety and ability, choſe rather to end
<pb facs="tcp:103564:3"/>their dayes in a howling Wilderneſs, than to defile themſelves with Idols. Learned <hi>Cotton</hi> anſwering the greateſt Prelate then living, that <hi>Cultus, non Inſtitutus,</hi> was Idolatry. But becauſe ſome who have been Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors have now their eyes opened, with taſting the Hony of Preferment, Gain and Security, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore will not take the Perſons before mentioned as competent Witneſſes in the Caſe; I might ſummon in a Jury of the ableſt Conformiſts in former dayes, to give in their Verdict, for the Araignment &amp; Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation of Invented Worſhip. In a word, all out Proteſtant Writers, who contend with the Papiſts, do uſe the ſame Arguments againſt their numerous Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly-dayes, their Oyl-Criſme, their Holywater, Maſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as we do againſt Holy-dayes, and other retained Services and Ceremonies: But becauſe I will not keep you too long from the Banquet this Book pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents you with, take only a moſt famous Prophet of their own, the Learned Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> Dr. <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drews,</hi> in his Expoſition upon the Second Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment; his words are theſe. <q>
                  <hi>This Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which concerns the manner of Worſhip, contains a Precept ſet down by way of Prohibition in theſe words, NON FACIES TIBI SCULPTILE: The Sanction in theſe words, EGO ENIM DEUS TUUS SUM ZE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LOTYPUS. Shewing how they ſhall be corrected that will not be directed by this Law.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Concerning the Performance of this Worſhip, two things are commanded, firſt, God will have MODUM
<pb facs="tcp:103564:4"/>A SE PRESCRIPTUM. Our ſervice muſt be done in that manner himſelf preſcribes.</hi> Non ſimulacrum, non Imago damnatur ſed non facies tibi, <hi>thou ſhalt not make</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Invented and Will-Worſhip, deviſed by Man, is here forbidden. — Men would have Worſhip of their own, whereas God hath told them, whatſoever thing I command you, obſerve to do it; thou ſhalt not add thereto, nor diminiſh from it.</hi> Hoc tantum facere, quod Deus precepit; <hi>and he brings in a reaſon aſſigned by</hi> Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtom, Qui honoratur, is maxime eo honore de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectatur, quem ipſe vult, non quem nos volumus, non eſt honor, ſed dedecus, ſi vel contra, vel pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter mandatum fiat. <hi>It is rather a diſgrace than honour to God, to Worſhip him either againſt or beſides his own Rule.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Since therefore you have ſuch a Cloud of Witneſſes, let us run with patience our preſent race, &amp; follow them who through great Tribulation have adhered to <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> If you can ſtand before the wrath of a jealous God, if you can drink the dreggs of the Cup of his fury, then adventure upon <hi>Worſhip of a humane Original and Generation.</hi> But I leave you to the conſcientious peruſal of the enſuing Diſcourſe, which is full fraught with cogent Arguments, for the Authority of <hi>Jeſus Coriſt,</hi> and againſt the frothy Impoſitions of defiling Inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in the <hi>Worſhip of God.</hi> The Lord grant that the living <hi>Words</hi> of this <hi>Dead Saint,</hi> may be <hi>bleſſed</hi> to the purpoſe by him intended, to the awakening of ſome who are now ſnore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Lap of the
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Nah.</hi> 3.4.</note> well-favoured Harlot, and to the eſtabliſhment of others in the preſent Truth.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>C. W.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:103564:4"/>
            <head>Common-Prayer-Book Devotions, Epiſcopal Deluſions: OR, The ſecond Death of the Service-Book.</head>
            <p>THE Liturgy, or Common-Prayer (commonly uſed in our Pariſh Churches) relateth unto the conſcience of him that uſeth it, and of him that deſireth to be underſtandingly ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied about the lawfulneſs or unlawfulneſs of the uſe of it, both in the matter and form, or ſubſtance, but eſpecially in the injun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction or impoſition of it by men. I ſhall (at preſent) not ſay much unto it in the former relation; only, in caſe the impoſition were taken off, and Miniſters and People left at full liberty, the one whether they would read it, the other whether they would attend upon it or no; theſe (amongſt many other) particulars would be very conſiderable.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Whether God, under the New Teſtament, or ſince <hi>Chriſt</hi> aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded on high to give gifts unto men, ever commanded, or required, or ſpake a word of ſuch a thing? or, whether ever <hi>it came into his mind, or heart,</hi> (Jer. 7.31. &amp; 19.5.) to be worſhipped by his Saints in their Publick Aſſemblies, by a ſtinted form of Liturgy and Prayers, not to be altered or varied from, from generation to generation, upon any imergencies of Providence whatſoever, unleſs the Powers and Potentates of the Earth ſhall interpoſe with their Swords and Scepters to command it? and conſequently, whether they who draw near unto him in this Worſhip, have not as much cauſe to fear the breaking-out of his Jealouſie upon them, as <hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abihu</hi> had for <hi>offering ſtrange fire before the Lord, which he commanded them not?</hi> (Levit. 10.1.) and whether the patience and long-ſuffering of God, exerciſed towards perſons offending in this kind in theſe dayes, be not to <hi>lead them to repentance?</hi> Rom. 2.4.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Whether, in caſe it were (or, upon good grounds, could be) ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, that it may be pleaſing enough unto God to be worſhipped by his Saints in their holy Aſſemblies, with ſet forms of Liturgies and Prayers, being left free, and not impoſed, [namely if they be, for mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and form, irreprovable, or ſuch as they may be] it could notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding reaſonably be ſuppoſed withall, that Worſhip according to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:103564:5"/>any model or draught of Liturgy, or Prayers whatſoever, would be thus pleaſing unto him; More particularly, whether a Worſhip, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form to the image of ſuch a Liturgy, as we ſhall now characterize, or deſcribe (in part) would be in any degree pleaſing unto him; as <hi>viz.</hi> 1. which ſhall be a rhapſody, medley, or confuſed heap of a multitude of ingredients, heterogeneal, and of oppoſit natures,
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Mollia cum duris, ſine pondere habentia pondus,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Things ſoft and hard, things weighty, and things light,</l>
               </q> (as the Poet deſcribes the conſtirution of the old <hi>Chaos</hi>) no more meet to be moulded together into the ſame body of an Evangelical Worſhip, than God under the Law judged an Ox or an Aſs to be yoked together for ſervice in the ſame plough; as for inſtance, Canonicals, and <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criphals,</hi> the heavenly ſayings of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and the fabulous reports of <hi>To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit,</hi> the Pſalms of <hi>David,</hi> and the Song of S. <hi>Ambroſe, Magnificat,</hi> and <hi>Quicunque vult,</hi> paſſages and expreſſions, ſome grave and ſerious, ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid and diſtinct; others, ludicrous and light, barbarous, obſcure and truthleſs. 2. Wherein the Prayer-devotion preſcribed, is, or ſhall be, ordered with that ſtrange unſutableneſs to the ſimplicity of the Goſpel, that 1. the Lord's Prayer, which was delivered by him with a ſpecial intent to prevent battologies, or vain repetitions in prayer, (<hi>Mat.</hi> 6.7, 8, 9. compared) is it ſelf injoyned to be repeated, over, and over, and over, (and I know not how often) without any reaſon given (or eaſie to be taken) for any one of theſe repetitions in their reſpective places: this diſpoſition of it can be reſolved into no other reaſon or cauſe, but the meer phanſy and will of the Contriver, who by it, ſeems to have been acted by the ſpirit of this ſuperſtition (condemned by Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.7.) that men ſhall <hi>be heard for their much ſpeaking,</hi> or for the tale and number of their prayers, only ſaid over and repeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Beſides, this Prayer is ordered to be at the ſame time audibly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced by all the Congregation and Miniſter together, in ſome of the ſaid places. Again, 2. the great body of this Prayer-devotion is ſo ill handled (not to mention the unſound conſtitution in ſeveral veins and parts of it) that it is divided in ſunder, and ſome parts of it ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered from others, in ſeveral places, by Pſalms and Songs, by Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and broken pieces of Chapters (under the falſe titles of <hi>Epiſtles</hi> and <hi>Gospels,</hi> whereof they are but ſmall ſnips or ſhreds) by <hi>Creeds</hi> or Confeſſions of Faith thruſt in between: and beſides, it is in ſome pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, chopped or minced into ſmall pieces or particles, and a diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them made, ſome to the Miniſter and ſome to the People, as if the People were to be the mouth of the Miniſter unto God, as well as he theirs in the publick Aſſemblies: yea, when Miniſter and People
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:103564:5"/>are acting their parts in theſe ſtrains of Prayer interchangeably aſſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto them, there is ſuch a bandying and toſſing of devotions to and again, from one to the other, in a gingling and mymmical manner, that it much reſembles the jolly ſcene of a ſet of Ale-inſpired Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions, chanting their drunken Catches upon a bench. 3. Where this great body of praying-devotion is compounded and made up of many leſſer bodies of prayers, the greateſt part of which are more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire and diſtinct bodies in this kind, than the main body or bulk ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, made up of them all, being cloſed and ſealed up (reſpectively;) with ſo many <hi>Amens.</hi> Which is a method, or manner of praying, no where recommended unto us in the Scriptures by the Holy Ghoſt. 4. Where there are appropriate devotions, as Prayers (under the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocryphal name of <hi>Collects</hi>) Epiſtles, Goſpels, ſelect Chapters, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for ſeveral dayes (forced by the unjuſt hand of humane powers; out of that allowance of ſix dayes in the week, which God himſelf was pleaſed to make unto men, to provide themſelves by their honeſt labour of things needful for this preſent life, and dedicated by men to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and ſervice of certain Saints long ſince dead) and ſo theſe days, though but of humane conſecration, are here made equal in all points with the Lord's days themſelves. 5. Where the Service preſcribed and enjoyned under the ſpecious pretext of being <hi>Divine,</hi> conſiſting of ſhort pieces or Sentences of Scriptures, of a Confeſſion of Sins, of an Abſolution, of the Lords Prayer, repeated, and repeated, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated; and ſo of the Doxology (ſo called) in like manner repeated, over, and over, and over; of whole Chapters for Leſſons, of broken Chapte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s for Epiſtles and Goſpels; of pieces of Chapters, as <hi>Magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficat, Benedictus, Nunc dimittis,</hi> &amp;c. (with the Song of S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Ambroſe</hi>) to ſeparate between Leſſon and Leſſon (as if there were ſome danger, or inconvenience at leaſt, if they ſhould come too cloſe together) of the Ten Commandments, with as many <hi>Lord have mercy upon us's;</hi> of a long Letany (ſo called) of Verſicles and Reſponds, of Collects and Prayers in abundance, ſome for all men, ſome for Chriſts Church <hi>mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant</hi> here on Earth, ſome for Biſhops, Paſtors and Curates, (as if theſe were Members of the Church <hi>triumphant</hi>) and ſome for ſuch other oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions as the Policy and Piety of the Compilers could agree upon) and laſtly of a pair of Creeds, the repeating of one of which being required of the whole Congregation, requireth the moſt ignorant and prophane wretch in it, to profeſs and ſay that he believeth as much (if not more) as the moſt knowing and worthieſt <hi>Chriſtian;</hi> yea, and that he believeth that which I believe no man underſtandeth upon any good grounds what it meaneth, (I mean that <hi>Chriſt deſcended into Hell</hi>) the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:103564:6"/>other impoſing upon all men ſuch a Faith as of abſolute neceſſity unto Salvation, which the Scriptures no where require upon ſuch terms, of any man, and which is not found in many ſound <hi>Christians,</hi> if in any. Where (I ſay) the Service enjoyned, conſiſting of all theſe Members and Parts now mentioned, muſt needs be tedious and tire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome unto the People, ſpending and waſting the beſt and freſheſt of their attention, and ſo indiſpoſing them to attend unto the preaching of the Goſpel, and the words by which they muſt be ſaved: as if the project and deſign of it had been to intercept the great Duties of prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching and hearing the Goſpel preached, by rendring the wearied Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter leſs capable of the one, and the wearied People leſs capable and deſirous of the other. Now then, I repeat from afar, and ask, Is it not very conſiderable (or rather indeed is it worth any conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at all?) whether God will be pleaſed with a Worſhip preſented unto him in the ſhape and form of ſuch a prodigious Liturgy as that which hath now been deſcribed? unleſs (haply) men think that a Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip made up of various pieces, and theſe of different colours, is as honourable, and ſo as acceptable unto God, as <hi>Jacob</hi> thought a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coloured Coat would be unto <hi>Joſeph</hi> his Son: Or doth not the Liturgy, the lineaments and feature of which have been preſented, as perfectly reſemble the Common-Prayer-Book, as <hi>face anſwereth face in the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. It calls for ſome conſideration likewiſe, whether it be poſſible (in an ordinary way, or without a piece of a miracle) for a man or a woman, to keep up his heart ſo much as in a tolerable poſture of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion, reverence, and attention unto ſuch prayers, which having been fram'd by men, and theſe not of any known excellency above their neighbours, are, in reſpect of their original, leſs conſiderable, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter long familiarity more obnoxious to contempt, eſpecially when he can (well nigh) ſay them by roat beforehand, and of which he is able to ſay (with him in the Comedy) <hi>Plus millies jam audivi,</hi> I have heard them more than a thouſand times over already. The common ſaying (verified by experience more than enough) is, <hi>familiarity breeds con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt</hi> and neglect. And God himſelf judgeth it neceſſary to conſult his Glory, [I mean, a religious awe, reverence, and eſteem of his Counſels and Works from men] by concealing the one and the other, until the time of their bringing forth, that ſo they may come freſh and new unto them. <hi>It is the Glory of God to conceal a thing,</hi> Pro. 25.2. And ſpeaking of his Works (<hi>Iſa.</hi> 48.7.) <hi>They are created now, and not of old, and even before this thou heardeſt them not,</hi> (ſo the former Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation) <hi>lest thou ſhould ſay, Behold, I knew them;</hi> implying, that men
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:103564:6"/>(commonly at leaſt) leſs mind or regard the declaration of ſuch things unto them which they knew before. And upon this account (doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs) our Saviour ſpeaketh thus (<hi>Mat.</hi> 13.52.) <hi>Therefore every Scribe [i.e.</hi> every Doctor, or Teacher] <hi>which is inſtructed unto</hi> [or, for] <hi>the Kingdom of Heaven,</hi> [<hi>i.e.</hi> is worthily or meetly qualified for the work of the Miniſtry of the Goſpel, by which the Kingdom of Heaven is promoted in the world] <hi>is like unto a man that is an houſholder, which bringeth forth out of his treaſure things new and old.</hi> Now an ability to pray, being as neceſſary an endowment for a worthy Miniſter of the Goſpel, as a gift of preaching, the Apoſtles themſelves (as it ſeems, <hi>Act.</hi> 6.4.) giving it the preheminence in the exerciſe of their Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry: that Miniſter who ſhall pray little, but only reade a longſome beadroll of Prayers long and ſhort, (if yet they may be called <hi>Prayers,</hi> ſome of them being termed <hi>Collects;</hi> the greater part or number of them being imbodied, and this body ſirnamed <hi>Letany</hi>) a work, the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance whereof requires not the beſt of the abilities of an ordinary Schoolboy of ſeven years of age, and therefore very improper and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comly for him to beſtow ſo much time upon, who ſhould be, yea and who pretends to be an Ambaſſador from Chriſt unto the World, one of a thouſand, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſuch a Miniſter, I ſay, that ſhall perform the praying part of his Miniſtry at ſuch a deſpicable rate as this, is not like to draw many into part and fellowſhip with him in his worſhip of God, but ſuch who know not that God whom they worſhip, nor care much either to know him, or how to worſhip him as they ought. The igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, the prophaneneſs, the wickedneſs, the licentious and debauched lives of the greateſt part of that generation, both men and women, who are the zealous followers of the Common-Prayer-Book Miniſtry in the Nation, will ſeal the truth of theſe ſayings faſt and ſure.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Neither is this to be lightly paſſed over by thoſe that ſtand in any awe or dread of the jealouſie of God, that the <hi>Liturgy</hi> or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Prayer we ſpeak of, ſmells rank of the Popiſh Maſs-Book, being (indeed ſome ſlight interpolations, or new ſurbuſhings, with ſome ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodations to ſecular or civil ends and purpoſes amongſt us, only excepted) little elſe but the ſubſtance, matter, &amp; contents of this Book. This conſideration alone is ſufficient to render it the abhorring of their ſouls, that underſtand any thing (almoſt) of the nature and dreadful ſeverity of divine jealouſie; as that any little ſpark, not only of right-down or broad-fac'd Idolatry, but of any tiffling dalliance, or wanton compliance with it, will cauſe it to ſmoke againſt thoſe that ſhall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke it in this kind. Husbands that are jealous, are not able to bear, not only the groſs act of Adultery in their Wives, but not ſo much as
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:103564:7"/>any familiarity or correſpondence, any light or looſe behaviour, with known Adulterers, or perſons ſtrongly ſuſpected of that Wickedneſs. Under the Law God ſtrictly prohibited ſuch things unto his People, which were in themſelves lawful enough, (though not neceſſary) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they were obſerved by their idolatrous Neighbours. See, read, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider and compare at leiſure, <hi>Levit.</hi> 19.27, 28. &amp; 21.5, 6. Deut. 14.1, 2. with <hi>Iſa.</hi> 15.2. <hi>Jer.</hi> 48.37. &amp; 9.26. &amp; 25.23. &amp; 49.32. (according to the import of the Original, noted in the margent of your larger Bibles, at theſe three laſt Texts) and <hi>Deut.</hi> 12.30. they are charged by him not to ask or enquire, <hi>How did theſe Nations</hi> [being idolatrous] <hi>ſerve their gods, that I may do ſo likewiſe?</hi> And in the New Teſtament, Chriſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth upon the practice of the Gentiles, as an argument to diſſwade his Diſciples from taking thought for outward things, <hi>For after all theſe things do the Gentiles ſeek,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.32. Beſides, for Saints to bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row of a ſuperſtitious, wicked and idolatrous Generation, Enemies unto God, and to all that truly love and fear him, a Model or Plat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form of Worſhip to be preſented unto him, by which they have (in conjunction with other unhallowed Artifices) ſupported, nouriſhed, and kept up an Antichriſtian Intereſt for a long time in the World; when as they [the Saints] have the manifold Wiſdom of God before them in the Scriptures, and may have his Spirit alſo for the asking, to direct and teach them how to worſhip and ſerve him acceptably, from time to time, muſt needs, in the eye of Reaſon it ſelf, be ſpiritually unnatural, and moſt unbecoming thoſe who pretend to the high honour and dignity of being Children of Light. The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> pleads this twice together, by way of bar to the eating of things offered unto Idols, by Chriſtians; <hi>The Earth is the Lords, and the fulneſs thereof,</hi> 1 Cor. 10.26, 28. The connexion of this reaſon, with that which he deſires to perſwade unto by it, is this, It is moſt unworthy the Sons and Daughters of God, to defile themſelves with eating the Devils meat, [that which hath been ſacrificed and given unto him] whereof he hath no great plenty neither, whenas their Father is Lord and Owner of a world of Proviſions clean and wholeſome, wherewith they have no cauſe to fear or doubt but that he will ſufficiently ſupply them. And of thoſe who did or ſhould preſume to eat of the Devils portion, he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth argumentatively, and with great earneſtneſs and vehemency of ſpirit, thus: <hi>Do we provoke the Lord unto Jealouſie?</hi> [that is, to the fierceſt of his diſpleaſure againſt us] <hi>Are we ſtronger than he?</hi> [meaning otherwiſe that we are not like to eſcape the ſeverity of his anger, if we continue ſo to provoke him] 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.22. Is it not altogether as ill conſiſtent with the Wiſdom, Honour, and Peace of Believers in theſe
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:103564:7"/>days to be found of that Worſhip which hath been deviſed, contrived, formed and faſhioned (no man knows by what Rule, nor by whoſe Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections) by men juſtly given up by God unto ſtrong deluſions, and to <hi>believe</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that <hi>Lie</hi> of Lies, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.11. and to walk in <hi>abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Idolatries</hi> (as <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaketh) whenas God, in and by the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and ſupplies of his Spirit, hath vouchſafed unto them means and opportunities in abundance to inable themſelves to worſhip him with a Worſhip pure and clean, no ways charged or encumbred with any ſuſpicion or jealouſie of Satans interpoſure with the leaſt of his Fingers in the moulding and framing of it.</p>
            <p>That which is commonly pretended to hide the baſeneſs of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentage or Original of the <hi>Liturgy</hi> impleaded, is but a vail that is tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſparent, and eaſily ſeen thorow, by thoſe that are willing to examine it, and look a little narrowly into it. For the Martyrs, and other pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and learned men, in whoſe weakneſs the importune Commenders and Obtruders of this Liturgy (our apocryphal Lord Biſhops, with thoſe that are younger Brethren in the ſame iniquity with them) do ſo much glory for advantage ſake, as if they were the Fathers or Compilers of it; the truth is, they were neither ſo, nor ſo, unleſs in a diminutive ſenſe onely, and that which is not much conſiderable for their pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. And if they had been as deſirous to honour thoſe Martyrs and pious men they ſpeak of, as they are to exalt themſelves, they ſhould, with the good Sons of <hi>Noah,</hi> have caſt ſome covering over their naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and not publiſh it upon all occaſions, as now they do, unto the world; with an intent to cover, or rather to juſtifie their own by it. Some, afterwards Martyrs, and other good men, were (indeed) the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Liturgy, as ſuch, (I mean as <hi>Engliſh</hi>) and (haply) as wanting many ſtrains of that groſs Superſtition, Error and Idolatry which are ſound in the Latin <hi>Maſs-Book;</hi> and likewiſe as having ſome few things of leſſer moment added and inſerted by way of accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation to the Civil State; the <hi>Romiſh</hi> yoke, as well in Civil as Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtick affairs, having been newly caſt of by it. Nor do I doubt but that much may be pleaded, and this very Chriſtianly, for the juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of thoſe worthy and good men, in reſpect of the uprightneſs of their hearts, the honeſty and ſincerity of their intentions in the Work; who by a little refining of the ſaid Popiſh Devotions, and by altering the property of the Language wherein they were written, thought they might make them commodious enough for <hi>Engliſh</hi> Proteſtants: yea, and (probably) they might ſuppoſe that when they brought the Service of God (ſuch as it was, and they it ſeems eſteemed it ſuch as by a little purgation might be cleanſed from all the noyſom dregs of Popery, and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:103564:8"/>ſo become lawful) out of an unknown Tongue, into a Language which the People underſtood, they had (in a good ſence) brought <hi>light out of darkneſs,</hi> and ſo might be well apaid in their Conſciences with their Work. But though it be granted that they were perſons of eminent worth, both for their Piety and Learning, yet (queſtionleſs) they were no Prophets; or elſe the ſpirit of Prophecy failed them, in reference to the event and conſequence of their Common-Prayer-Book At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievement. For had they ſo much as once dreamed that this Book would prove ſuch a Root of Bitterneſs unto the Nation, as it is too well known it hath been; that it would create thoſe ſad diſtempers, thoſe diviſions, diſtractions, tumults, and confuſions, whereby both ſin and ſorrow have been abundantly encreaſed amongſt the inhabitants of the Land; or that it would be an Engine in the hands of men of unmer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful &amp; high-impoſing Spirits, wherewith to rack the Conſciences, and wreck the Comforts, Liberties, Eſtates, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of many thouſands of the Saints and dear Children of God in the <hi>Nation,</hi> being at this day employed, and like to be employed in theſe bloody executions, (unleſs the Righteouſneſs of God will pleaſe to reſtrain the remainder of the wrath of men.) Had (I ſay) the good men we ſpeak of, but once drea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of thoſe prodigies of miſchief whereunto our unhappy Service-Book hath been highly acceſſary, we may be groundedly confident that they would never have found either heart or hand to lift up toward the promoting of it. But in them is fulfilled the latter part of this old Diſtich:
<q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>:</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Good Fruit on bad Intendments ſometime grows;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And from good meanings ſometimes Evil flows.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. (And laſtly upon the preſent account) It is not unworthy his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration whoſe heart is firmly ſet within him to pleaſe God in wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping him, that the Liturgy or Prayer-Book, into which we are yet enquiring, is like unto a Net, which ſeldom encloſeth any good Fiſh, but multitudes and great ſholes of thoſe that are bad. It is ſufficiently known that the great body or bulk of thoſe that go wondering after it, and can ſavour no other kind or manner of Worſhip (at leaſt none comparatively) but that which the tradition of this Book teacheth them, are (more generally) men and women of one or more of theſe ſad cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters, ignorant, prophane, ſuperſtitious, time-ſervers, fearful, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believing, haters of thoſe that are good, Drunkards, Adulterers, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tortioners,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:103564:8"/>Covetous, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And though the proportion of <hi>one of a City, and two of a Tribe,</hi> of perſons of Conſcience, and truly fearing God, at whoſe Judgements and Conſciences the Convictions of the Unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of that Worſhip are not yet arrived, may be found in that Crowd; yet it is hardly credible that ſuch as theſe ſhould at any time partake in it with any great contentment, or good apayment of Soul. Perſons of crazy and ill-aboding Conſciences, eſpecially, if they be as well outwardly as inwardly obnoxious, are therefore (in all likeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood) ſo impotently devoted to the Book and Prayers we ſpeak of, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe theſe take pity on them, and intreat them gently; according to the common ſaying, <hi>Miſſa non mordet,</hi> THE MASS BITES NOT: It is not like unto the Spirit of God in the mouth of his able, faithful and zealous Miniſters, of a ſearching, expoſtulating, convincing, ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly-reproving nature; the ſound of it is not like that of Thunder, to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waken or terrifie men, but as the noiſe which a ſoft and gentle ſtream makes among Pebble Stones, which diſpoſeth unto ſleep.</p>
            <p>Now amongſt many Arguments which war ſtrongly againſt the ſaid Book, and Worſhip dictated therein, this (methinks) ſhould do thorow execution upon the Judgements and Conſciences of thoſe that are ſpiritually-minded, and make treaſure of the Love of God, <hi>viz.</hi> That they that are ſo zealouſly addicted unto them, even to the hatred and perſecution of thoſe that in the uſe of them cannot ſay <hi>Amen</hi> with them, are more generally, if not univerſally, perſons much eſtranged from the life of God, and affectionate lovers of this preſent world. For it is no light preſumption of the Carnality of a Worſhip, and that it is ſuch as pleaſeth not God, when it ſo pleaſeth his Enemies, (for ſuch are all thoſe that live not in ſubjection to his Laws, <hi>Luk.</hi> 19.27. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.7.) and withal, is of an uncouth and horrid taſte unto thoſe that <hi>love him and keep his Commandments.</hi> It is a ſign of the voice of a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and not of Chriſt, when the Sheep of Chriſt do not hear it, but ſlee from it, <hi>John</hi> 10.4, 5, 27. And the reaſoning of this Apoſtle (1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.5.) about matter of Doctrine, is as demonſtrative in the caſe of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip now before us: <hi>They are of the World</hi> [i. e. Teachers of whom I admoniſh you that you take heed, are of the ſame <hi>genius</hi> with the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality of men in the world, who love Eaſe, Pleaſure Riches, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, <hi>&amp;c.] therefore ſpeak they of the World,</hi> or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, out of, or from the world; [that is, they enquire and obſerve how matters go in the world, that ſo they may know how to promote their worldly Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, and accordingly they frame their Doctrines and Teachings:] <hi>And the World heareth them;</hi> [that is, perſons worldly-minded fall in readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and greedily with them, their Doctrine ſo well ſuiting their Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:103564:9"/>Diſpoſitions and Deſires.] So when a Form or Method of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip (for there is the ſame reaſon of Worſhip and Doctrine, as to the conſideration in hand, as was lately hinted) ſhall generally court and comport with the Humours, Fancies, and Conſciences (ſuch as they are) of looſe, ignorant, ſuperſtitious and earthly-minded-men, it is an argument concluding above all peradventure, that the complexion, frame and conſtitution of it anſwereth the <hi>genius,</hi> temper, and ſpirit of theſe men, much like as (in <hi>Solomon</hi>'s reſemblance) <hi>face anſwereth to face in the water.</hi> That manner or kind of Worſhip which God ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth and delighteth in, is not like to relliſh with the corrupt taſte of ſenſual and carnal men, any whit better then <hi>Paul</hi>'s preaching did <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>amongst thoſe that were loſt,</hi> [or rather <hi>periſhing,</hi> that is, in imminent danger of being loſt] to whom it was <hi>the ſavour of death unto death,</hi> (2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.16.) that is, it filled their Conſciences ever and anon with ſtrong reſentments of the wrath of God coming out againſt them like an armed man, to deſtroy them for their ſins. It is recorded of <hi>Antiſthenes,</hi> that when the unworthy multitude, contrary to their wonted manner of dealing by vertuous and worthy men, commended him, he expreſſed himſelf in this queſtion, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>? <hi>Alas, what evil have I done?</hi> If the Common-Prayer-Book did no evil, we may very reaſonably judge, that the great hoſt of the preſent Proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lytes and Admirers of it, would leave it as ſolitary as a Beacon on an hill. And it was the right ſaying of another, <hi>Recti argumentum eſt, peſſimis diſplicere;</hi> it is no light argument of the goodneſs whether of a perſon or thing, when thoſe that are very bad are diſpleaſed with either. <hi>Nero</hi>'s hatred of the Goſpel, was by ancient Chriſtians conſtrued as a teſtimony of the excellency and worth of it. Certainly the right and approved Worſhip, or way of worſhiping God, will never make glad the hearts of ſuch a Generation of men as now rejoyce in, and glory over the Book of Common-Prayer. But</p>
            <p n="2">2. Though theſe general conſiderations relating onely to the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and form, or ſubſtance of this Book (unto which many others of a more particular import, and drawn from the unmeet expreſſions and paſſages in it, which are very numerous, might be added upon the ſame account) are too conſiderable and weighty to be eaſily removed off the Judgements and Conſciences of ſerious and conſidering-men; yet the little finger of the impoſition of it, and of the Worſhip (ſo called) directed and held forth in it, is by many degrees heavier then the loyns of a thouſand ſuch conſiderations, and of a more tremend aſpect in the eye of every Conſcience that is enlightened, duely and clearly to apprehend the nature and conſequence of it. For ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:103564:9"/>the property of the Book ſhould be ſo far altered, that whereas it is now like the politick Body of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> State in <hi>Iſaiah</hi>'s days; <hi>The whole head is ſick, and the whole heart faint: from the ſoal of the foot even unto the head, there is no ſoundneſs in it, but wounds, and bruiſes, and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trifying ſores</hi> (Iſa. 1.5, 6.) Suppoſe (I ſay) it ſhould be ſo far altered from the preſent deformity and deplorable condition of it, as to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come as praiſe-worthy for Beauty as <hi>Abſalom,</hi> of whom it is ſaid, that <hi>from the ſoal of his foot even to the crown of his head there was no blemiſh in him,</hi> (2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 14.25.) and that a general Council of Elect Angels ſhould aſſemble to reform and amend it, and ſhould make all the crooked things in it ſtraight, and all the rough things in it ſmooth, yet would not this Angelical purity and perfection of it, (wherein its Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirers might in this caſe ſafely glory) juſtifie either the Impoſition of it from imperious Blaſphemy, or the uſe of it in worſhipping God, as, or becauſe impoſed, from baſe and wretched Idolatry.</p>
            <p>This is demonſtrable from this clear and pregnant ground, atteſted both by the Scriptures, and by the Light of Nature, or ſound Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Reaſon, conſonant to the Scriptures: <hi>It is as well or as much the incommunicable Priviledge or Prerogative of God, to preſcribe, appoint, and command his own Worſhip, as to be worſhipped;</hi> [I mean as to be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped in his <hi>Divine or God-like Capacity.</hi>] This being a Truth, (as we ſhall preſently, God aſſiſting, evince it to be) it undeniably, by a near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand conſequence, and whereof every man is or ſoon may be capable, followeth:</p>
            <p n="1">1. That he that ſhall authoritatively, under any penalty to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted on thoſe that ſhall not obey, command any Form, Model, Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod or manner of Divine Worſhip, to be obſerved by men, maketh himſelf God, or equal unto God, obtrudeth himſelf as God, or in Gods ſtead upon men, claiming, aſſuming, and uſurping ſuch a power, which is a branch of the appropriate and incommunicable prerogative of God. Even as he that claimeth and exerciſeth <hi>Regalia,</hi> ſuch Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and Authority, which are the appropriate Rights of Kings, maketh himſelf a King, and ſaith (in effect, and in a more ſignificant expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion then the plaineſt words that way would amount unto) I am a King. In like manner whoever acteth or exerciſeth any of thoſe Divine Rights, Authorities, or Powers, which are inſeparably annexed to the Throne of Heaven, and ſo declared and aſſerted by him that ſitteth thereon; though in words he ſhould deny it, yet in deeds, which ſpeak loudeſt, he profeſſeth and ſaith, I am God. It is like that they who ſtumble at this ſtone, may think they walk inoffenſively in their way; and (probably) intend no ſuch thing as an arrogation of Divinity unto
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:103564:10"/>themſelves in what they do: But this is common to the greateſt Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders of all, not to intend the formality, but onely the matter of their wicked actions; to intend onely the Text, not the interpretation of their ſins: The groſſeſt Idolater that is, doth not intend to commit the ſin of Idolatry; but he intends the doing of that, which being truly interpreted, is the committing of the ſin of Idolatry. There is the like conſideration of the Blaſphemer, of the Perſecutor of the Saints, and of many other moſt enormous Tranſgreſſors: And thus it is like to be with thoſe who count it a goodly thing to ſay with the King of <hi>Babel</hi> of old, <hi>We will aſcend above the heights of the Clouds, WE WILL BE LIKE UNTO THE MOST HIGH,</hi> (Iſa. 14.14.) We will give Laws to the Judgements and Conſciences of Men, as well as He: It is like (I ſay) that though they ſpeak thus in their actions, yet they do not intend to make themſelves Corrivals in Authority and Power with God, or to ſuperſede and make void his Laws concerning his Worſhip, with devotional Laws and Statutes of their own. From the ſaid ground it clearly alſo followeth:</p>
            <p n="2">2. That whoſoever ſhall accept of, ſubmit unto, or worſhip God with, any ſuch Worſhip, or form of Worſhip, which is preſcribed, impoſed, and commanded by men (eſpecially if he ſhall ſubmit unto it, as, or becauſe thus commanded) committeth ſpiritual whordom, and bringeth the heavy guilt of the ſin of Idolatry upon his ſoul (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the ſtrengthening the hand of the impoſer in a very ſinful way) The reaſon hereof, upon the former ground, is plain: namely, becauſe he exhibiteth that honour, reverence, and homage unto a creature, which are due unto God alone, and (as it were) turns creature unto him that is no God, unleſs a God may be made of duſt and aſhes. For if it be the Prerogative of God to appoint and command his own wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, they who approve and juſtifie men aſſuming and exerciſing this Prerogative, entertain the creature with divine reverence and honour, ſaying (conſtructively, and in effect) unto it, Thou art God, or, I acknowledge and own thee for my God. Perſons of this Character are all thoſe, who practiſe the Worſhip commanded by men, upon the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, or becauſe of their command; whether they do it willingly, I mean, before, or without any outward violence, or compulſion; or whether they do it upon ſufferings, or through ſear of ſuffering; though the ſin ſeems to be much greater in the former caſe. <hi>Ephraim is oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and broken in Judgment, becauſe he WILLINGLY</hi> [that is, readily, and with forwardneſs of compliance, without asking any que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion for conſcience ſake] <hi>walked after the commandment</hi> [meaning after the idolatrous commandment of their King <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> ſeconded
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:103564:10"/>and enforced by all his ſucceſſors.] <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 5.9. He that liveth under the Authority and Government of a lawful King over him, and ſhall ſubject himſelf unto the commands of another, commanding him as his King, or ſuch things, which his King only hath, by the Laws, a right of Authority and Power to command him, renounceth his Allegiance unto his own Prince, and becomes a Traitor to his Crown and Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</p>
            <p n="3">3. From the ground aforeſaid, it followeth yet further, that ſuch perſons who do obey the Commands of their Princes, or other Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, wherein they enjoyn them any form, method, or manner of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Worſhip, are in ſuch their obedience, their greateſt enemies, thereby expoſing them to the ſtroke of the jealouſie, and high diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of God. The reaſon of this conſequence is, becauſe to make an Idol of any creature, or to ſet up any, whether thing or perſon, in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petition with God, and to aſcribe divine honour unto it, rendreth it the object of his ſevere wrath and jealouſie. The Scripture is abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly pregnant with teſtimony of this truth, as well in the caſe of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons as of things. The People aſcribing divine honour unto <hi>Herod,</hi> in giving a ſhout in applauſe of his Oration, <hi>The voice of God and not of man,</hi> brought ſuddain deſtruction upon him, and this in a moſt loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom and grievous manner: <hi>And immediately</hi> (ſaith the text) <hi>the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel of the Lord ſmote him, becauſe he gave not God the glory</hi> [whereby he might indeed have prevented the judgment] <hi>and he was eaten of worms, and gave up the ghoſt,</hi> Acts 12.22, 23. So dangerous a thing it is for Princes, and Great men to accept of divine honour, when it is caſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them: how much more when they ſhall themſelves compel men by threatning Laws and Edicts, to aſcribe it unto them (as all they do, who by ſevere mulets and penalties conſtrain men to worſhip God, not as he pleaſeth, or commandeth, but as they pleaſe themſelves.) It was not ſimply <hi>Jeroboams</hi> Idolatry, nor yet his Edict or Command unto the People, to worſhip his Idol-Calves, but it was the compliance of his People with this Command, that occaſioned his ruine, and the rooting out of his Houſe and Poſterity (as it did likewiſe occaſion the like miſery to all his Succeſſors; yea, and the utter ruine of his whole State and Kingdom in a ſhort time) This is clear from the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs tenor of the context, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 12.30. compared with <hi>verſ.</hi> 34. of the following Chapter. In the former place we read thus: <hi>And this thing</hi> [namely, <hi>Jeroboam's</hi> ſetting up his two Calves, <hi>verſ.</hi> 28, 29.] <hi>became a ſin;</hi> or, <hi>turned to ſin</hi> (as our former tranſlation had it) mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that in time, and this not very long neither, it <hi>became ſin to the houſe of Jeroboam, even to cut it off, and to deſtroy it from off the face of the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:103564:11"/>earth.</hi> It was a ſin ſimply, yea, a very great ſin, as ſoon as it was acted: that is, the ſetting up of the Calves, and the preſſing of the People to worſhip them, was a great ſin in <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> whatſoever the conſequence of it had been, or whether the People had worſhipped them or no, or though, himſelf repenting of it, it had not been his ruine. But it did not <hi>BECOME</hi> a ſin of that ſad conſequence, as to be deſtructive to <hi>Jerohoam</hi> and his houſe, but by means of the Peoples compliance with him in it, as is manifeſt from the former place, where this (in the latter part of the verſe) is rendred as a reaſon, or an account, why and how <hi>Jeroboams</hi> act in ſetting up the Calves, and cauſing the People to worſhip them, <hi>became</hi> a ſin of that heavy conſequence unto him, <hi>viz.</hi> that the People (generally) approved and practiſed that worſhip: <hi>And this became a ſin: for the People went to worſhip, before the one, even unto Dan,</hi> or, as far as <hi>Dan;</hi> [implying it ſeems, that the King him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and his Nobles, and Attendants, worſhipped before the other, which was ſet up in <hi>Bethel,</hi> the Kings Court or Chappel being here, <hi>Amos</hi> 7.13. Or elſe it may import the great zeal and forwardneſs of the People in comporting with their King in his Idolatrous Worſhip, and that even thoſe of them that dwelt in <hi>Bethel,</hi> and in places near to it, would needs travel as far as <hi>Dan,</hi> which was at the furtheſt diſtance from <hi>Bethel</hi> the Land would afford, to worſhip before the Calf ſet up there, that in <hi>Bethel</hi> not being prepared and fitted for ſuch Devotion till ſome while after, as may be gathered from verſ. 32, 33.] From which paſſages compared, it plainly appears that had not the People obeyed him in his idolatrous device, it might have been a lengthning out of his Tranquillity, and his Poſterity after him might have ſat up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Throne: Yea, and (probably) it might through the Bleſſing of God, have proved a means or occaſion of his Repentance. It is not unlike but that <hi>Jeroboam</hi>'s Prieſts, made of the baſeſt of the People, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving once taſted of the Kings Favour and bountiful Allowance ſettled upon their Prieſthood, ſtrengthned his hand all they could, in his Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous Worſhip, bewitching him with this, or ſome ſuch lying and dangerous notion as this; <hi>No Calves, no King;</hi> (even as thoſe who are known by the Name of Biſhops, but not by the properties or works of Biſhops indeed, being advanced unto large Revenues and much worldly Pomp and Power by Chriſtian Kings, are very ſolicitous and careful to nouriſh this prepoſterous and importune conceit in them up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all occaſions, <hi>No Biſhop, no King</hi>) But as unto <hi>Jeroboam, Calves and no King,</hi> had been the more prudential and ſafe Maxime of State; not the want or pulling down of his Calves, but the ſetting of them up, being the true and real cauſe (as we lately heard from the Records of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:103564:11"/>the holy Ghoſt himſelf) why after a ſhort time he was <hi>no King,</hi> nor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of his houſe long after him: So is it more then conjecture, that BISHOPS, AND NO KING, would make the far better Article in the Politick Creed of Chriſtian Kings, and more worthy to be believed than the contrary, <hi>No Biſhop, no King.</hi> But this by the way. It hath been ſhewed from the Scriptures, that to idolize a Perſon, or to aſcribe Divine Honour unto any man, either directly (as the People did unto <hi>Herod</hi>) or indirectly, (as the Ten Tribes did unto <hi>Jeroboam</hi> their King, in accepting that way of worſhipping God, which he preſcribed unto them) is to awaken the eye of Divine Jealouſie upon him, unleſs he refuſeth or diſclaimeth it when it is tender'd unto him: which though Angels and holy Men have always done, yet it hath not been the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom or manner of Kings and Great Men in the World ſo to do. <hi>Jacob</hi> (we know) loved his Wiſe <hi>Rachel</hi> very tenderly and affectionately; yet when ſhe required of him that which was proper onely unto God to give, and ſo reflected Divine Honour upon him, <hi>[Give me Children or elſe I die]</hi> he being (as it ſeems) ſuddenly ſtruck with the apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the danger which ſuch a ſaying might expoſe him unto, reproveth her ſharply for her inconſiderateneſs therein; but withal, amandeth and diſpatcheth away that Divine Honour which was put upon him, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him who was the right owner of it: <hi>Am I</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>in Gods ſtead?</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Gen.</hi> 30.1, 2.</p>
            <p>And as they who comply with Kings and Rulers in their Commands concerning Forms of Worſhip of humane device, are in ſuch their complyance great Enemies unto them; ſo on the other hand, they who chuſe rather to abide the bittereſt blaſt of their diſpleaſure, then to pleaſe them with conforming themſelves to their wills and pleaſures in ſuch caſes, are in this detrectation of their Obedience unto them, their real Friends. Thus <hi>Daniel,</hi> notwithſtanding his refuſal to obey the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree of King <hi>Darius,</hi> being unlawful, ſaid unto him, <hi>Alſo unto thee,</hi> (or againſt thee) <hi>O King have I done no hurt,</hi> Dan. 6.22. In which words he ſeems as well to imply that they who had obeyed him in that his Decree, had been unfaithful unto him, had caſt a ſnare upon him, and done him harm; as to aſſert his own integrity and goodneſs of heart towards him: And that the holy man was ſo far from doing any <hi>hurt</hi> to the King by changing his Command, that he did him much good by it, appears by the ſequel of the Chapter, where we und hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, by means hereof, enlightned with the knowledge of the true God, and giving a full teſtimony to his excellent Greatneſs and Power, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commending his Worſhip and Service unto all his Dominions, verſ. 26, 27. Of like happy conſequence unto King <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> was the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:103564:12"/>like diſobedience of thoſe three faithful Servants of God and the King, <hi>Shadrach, Meſhach,</hi> and <hi>Abednego,</hi> in refuſing to ſubmit to his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand about the worſhipping of his Golden Image, <hi>Dan.</hi> 3.28, 29.</p>
            <p>Again, That other Creatures, whether animate or inanimate, by being contrived or converted into Idols, or veſted with any honour appropriate unto God, are hereby prepared for the ſwifter deſtruction, by reaſon of the Jealouſie of God, the Scriptures teſtifie yet more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly. Notwithſtanding I ſhall not inſiſt upon this at preſent, but mention one place onely, and point at others: <hi>And the ſtrong ſhall be as tow,</hi> [that is, the Idols, though made of never ſo ſtrong and dura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble materials, as Iron, Braſs, Stone, Silver, Gold, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or rather <hi>the Strong,</hi> that is, the Idols in which you put your confidence, ſuppoſing them to be ſtrong and able to protect you againſt all dangers, ſhall be as the moſt light and combuſtible matter, not able to make the leaſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance againſt the fire, when it is put to it] <hi>and the Maker of it as a ſpark,</hi> [that is, they that made them Idols, by this very contrivance of them, ſhall be the means or occaſion of their breaking to pieces, their defacement, or ſtamping to powder: even as they that make Idols of men, as was lately ſhewed, do hereby occaſion, and haſten their ruine] <hi>and they ſhall both burn together,</hi> [Idol, and Idol-maker, ſhall be deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed together, <hi>i. e.</hi> as well one, as the other] <hi>and none ſhall quench them:</hi> [that is, they ſhall certainly periſh, what means ſoever ſhall be made to preſerve, the one or the other] <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.31. See more of this Truth, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 18.4. <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.20. 2 <hi>King.</hi> 23.4, 5, 6, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 15.16. <hi>Jer.</hi> 10.11. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 2.18. <hi>Jer.</hi> 50.2. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 6.4, 6, 8, 11, 12.30.13. with others.</p>
            <p n="4">4. From the aforeſaid Principle or Ground it followeth likewiſe, That in caſe the greateſt and moſt lawful Authority amongſt men, ſhould under any civil penalty, or otherwiſe, impoſe upon thoſe under them, that very Worſhip, manner, or kind of Worſhip, which God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, either in his Word, or by the Law or Light of Nature, hath im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed on them; although this impoſition of it by men doth not render it unlawful, nor yet diſſolve the neceſſity of performing it, which the Law of God impoſeth on them: yet, if waving the Commandment of God in the caſe, they ſhall perform it meerly upon, and out of reſpect of the Commandment of men; and upon ſuch terms that they would not practiſe or perform it, did not their Superiours on Earth command it: ſuch a performance as this, even of the pureſt Worſhip that is, otherwiſe, would be idolatrous and unlawful: although this Worſhip, conſidered in it ſelf, or (in the School-expreſſion) <hi>in actu ſignato,</hi> would ſtill be the pure and true Worſhip of God. The reaſon of this conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence from the premiſes is, becauſe if it be the Prerogative or proper
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:103564:12"/>Right of God to command his own Worſhip, they who ſhall reject or diſown him in the claim hereof, and entertain or ſubmit unto any Creature claiming it, is like a Woman that admitteth a ſtranger into her husbands Bed, ſhutting him out of his own d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ors.</p>
            <p n="5">5. (And laſtly, for matter of conſequence) This concluſion alſo ſpringeth naturally from the ſame root with the former: That not to accept or ſubmit unto any Form or Model of Divine Worſhip, which hath been contrived and fram'd by men, can be no diſobedience to any Law, truly ſo called, in any politick State, Kingdom, or Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth whatſoever. The reaſon of this conſequence is pregnant and clear; namely, Becauſe there is, there can be no Law, truly and real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuch (I mean which hath the nature, eſſence, and binding force of a Law indeed) that requireth any thing of men, which is made or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared ſinful or unlawful by a ſuperiour Law. Any Act, Sanction, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree, Law, Statute or Conſtitution, which enjoyneth or impoſeth any thing contrary ei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>her to the Law or Mind of God in the Scriptures, or to the Law of Nature, or Light of Reaſon, by what Authority ſoever it be enacted, becomes void and null as ſoon as made, being like unto a Child that is ſtill born. Nor is this any ways repugnant to the Law of this Nation; the effect and ſubſtance of the notion being (as I un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand) the acknowledged ſence of ſome of the greateſt Lawyers themſelves, and will not (I preſume) be denied by any that underſtand themſelves like men in their Profeſſion. Yea, the <hi>Grand Debater</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf (though a man of as high an impoſing-ſpirit as Epiſcopal Zeal can lightly make him) acknowledgeth as much, in ſaying, <hi>'Tis true, a Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour cannot command a thing unlawful;</hi> Grand Debate, <hi>pag.</hi> 62. His meaning can be no other, but that when he doth command any ſuch thing, his Command is null, and not obliging: However, that Caſe is plain enough. Certain it is, that all Authority and Right of Power, is Originally veſted in God himſelf; and conſequently, that whatever Authority is ſeated in any Creature, one or more, they have it by deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation and gift from him, according to the Apoſtles Doctrine, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1. Again, As certain it is, that God giveth no Authority or Right of Power unto any man, or numbers of men whatſoever, againſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. Therefore no Act or Law (ſo called) whatſoever, that is made with repugnancy to his Intereſt of Authority, or Soveraignty of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding, hath the nature or force of a Law; the Makers of it, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they be, having received no Authority from God to make any ſuch: but on the contrary, ſtand charged by his Law to forbear all act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Law-making in that kind; yea, and lie under a ſevere threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning from him, in caſe they tranſgreſs: <hi>Wo unto them that decree un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:103564:13"/>Decrees,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 10.1. And as by the Laws of this Land, <hi>Nullum tempus occurrit Regi,</hi> There is no preſcription of Time againſt the King: ſo by the Law of Nature and common Reaſon, <hi>Nulla au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritas occurrit Regum Regi,</hi> No authority whatſoever, is of force a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the King of Kings. And as in the order and ſubordination of Civil Authorities, the Command of an inferiour Magiſtrate doth not bind againſt the Command of the Superiour, (ſuppoſing this to be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful;) the Warrant or Command of a Country Juſtice of Peace, is not to be obeyed (under the <hi>Proviſo</hi> mentioned) againſt the Order or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of a Judge; nor the Command of a Judge, againſt the lawful Command of the King. How much leſs doth the Authority of a weak and ſinful Creature, though the Name of it might be <hi>Legion,</hi> and they never ſo many, oblige any perſon againſt the leaſt <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or tittle of any the Commands or Laws of God, theſe being all unqueſtionably righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous and juſt? And as the Scripture teacheth us to reſolve the caſe without any demur or conſideration at all, between God and men, when they ſpeak contradictingly the one unto the other, ſo that the one muſt needs ſpeak truth, the other that which is falſe; <hi>Let God be true, and every man</hi> [whatſoever his intereſt or repute for truth be with men] <hi>a lyar</hi> (Rom. 3.4.) So when there is any inconſiſtency or conteſt between any of the Laws of God, and the Laws of men, the caſe is ſoon de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cided as concerning the equity or binding force of either; Let the Law of God be <hi>juſt, and holy, and good,</hi> and even upon this account alſo, chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge (with authority) obedience from men; but the Law of men un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt, unholy, and evil, and ſo a nullity, and of no authority at all to require ſubjection to it. Thus <hi>Peter</hi> (with other Apoſtles) in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the high Prieſt, and a great Council with him, was very po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive and definitive in the caſe, <hi>We ought rather to obey God, then men,</hi> Act. 5.29. not long before being, with <hi>John,</hi> brought as guilty perſons before another full Council, he judged the equity of the caſe ſo noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and broad on Gods ſide, that he feared not to make the Council it ſelf his Arbitrators, although they were Parties, and his Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries; <hi>Whether it be right in the ſight of God, to hearken unto you</hi> [or, <hi>to obey you,</hi> according to the former tranſlation] <hi>more</hi> [or, rather, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] <hi>than God, judge ye?</hi> Act. 4.19. So thoſe three Servants of God (lately mentioned) being commanded by King <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> to worſhip the Golden Image which he had ſet up, and in caſe of refuſal terribly threatned to be preſently caſt into the midſt of a fiery Furnace, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared unto him, That they <hi>were not careful to anſwer him in the matter,</hi> (Dan. 3.16.) the contrariety between the Kings Command, and the Command of God, was ſo manifeſt, that they required no time to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:103564:13"/>of an anſwer, or what to do in the caſe, but immediately reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to keep faſt and cloſe to the Command of God, though in ſo doing they muſt and did diſobey the Commandment of the King. Therefore if it be the Prerogative of God to appoint and command his own Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; that Law, or humane Conſtitution, which attempteth to diveſt him of it, and to communicate it unto any Creature, one, or more, or never ſo many, is indeed no Law, but an Uſurper of the name and ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of a Law, wanting the Spirit, Life, and Soul of a Law, which ſtand in an equitable force to bind to the obſervation of it. But no equity bindeth any man to give away the glory of God to another: So then, not to ſubmit to any form of Divine Worſhip, deviſed and impoſed by men, is to do the will of God, and conſequently not to tranſgreſs or diſobey any Law of man.</p>
            <p>Now for the demonſtration and proof of that Aſſertion, or Ground, (formerly mentioned) out of which the five Concluſions lately argued, grow as naturally, as ſo many Boughs or Arms of a Tree out of the Trunk or Body of it: Let us, firſt, hear, weigh, and conſider diligently and impartially, whether the Scriptures do not ſpeak to the heart of it, and whether God himſelf doth not here claim ſuch a Prerogative as therein is aſſerted unto him. Secondly, We ſhall conſult ſome of the Maximes of Nature, and Principles of Reaſon, about the truth of it.</p>
            <p>For the firſt. I intend not to inſiſt upon all places which offer themſelves willingly enough to ſerve in the preſent warfare: this would carry us far beyond the bounds of our intended brevity; but ſhall argue only ſome few of thoſe which ſpeak more plainly to our purpoſe.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Where God reproveth, rejecteth, or condemneth any Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, Form, or manner of Worſhip, upon this account, That <hi>He com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded it not;</hi> eſpecially when there are other things in it, one or more, very hateful and highly reproveable, he plainly declareth and aſſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it as his Prerogative, to appoint and command all Worſhip: Elſe why ſhould he make this the emphatical character of ſuch a Worſhip which his Soul abhorreth, <hi>That He commanded it not?</hi> eſpecially when this Worſhip is (as was now ſaid) otherwiſe, and in it ſelf, abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble? If men had any authority to appoint, or command a Worſhip, this were no reaſonable or juſt exception againſt any Worſhip whatſoever, <hi>That God commanded it not:</hi> but if it be juſtly reproveable, it muſt be for ſome intrinſecal evil either in the matter, or in the form of it, or in both. But paſſages of the import now ſpecified, the Scripture af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fordeth many: <hi>And they have built the high Places of Tophet, which is
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:103564:14"/>in the Valley of the ſons of Hinnom, to burn their ſons and their daughters in the fire, VVHICH I COMMANDED THEM NOT,</hi> Jer. 7.31. So again, <hi>They have built alſo the high-places of Baal, to burn their ſons with fire unto Baal, VVHICH I COMMANDED NOT, nor ſpake it, neither came it into my mind;</hi> Jer. 19.5. In both theſe places it is obſervable, that though the man-deviſed worſhip mentioned, was in it ſelf abominable, full of unnatural and barbarous cruelty, and beſides, performed to the honour of a moſt filthy and abominable Idol; yet God in reproving it, taketh no notice of either of theſe abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations, but inſiſts only upon this, that <hi>HE COMMANDED IT NOT,</hi> as being the greateſt abomination of all, and which (com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratively) juſtified all the reſt. Again; <hi>And they built the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>places of</hi> Baal, —<hi>VVHICH I COMMANDED THEM NOT, neither came it into my mind, that they ſhould do this abomination.</hi> Jer. 32.35. By comparing this expreſhon (in all theſe paſſages) <hi>VVHICH I COMMANDED THEM NOT,</hi> with the expreſs Command of God (Lev. 18.21.) <hi>Thou ſhalt not let any of thy ſeed paſs thorow the fire unto Molech,</hi> it plainly appears, that in the caſe of Worſhip, for God not to command and expreſly to forbid, are of one and the ſame conſideration: Even as in a Conveyance of Lands, whatſoever is not expreſſed, is no more conveyed than what is excepted. Yea, and it is very obſervable from the ſaid paſſages, that God intending to put the ſharpeſt accent upon the breach of his Law in the matter of Worſhip (which doubtleſs he doth intend in reproving and condemning it) He doth not place it in matter of ſimple diſobedience unto ſuch his Law (this being found in every ſin, I mean, diſobedience unto his Law, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.4.) but rather in the preſumption of men to attempt any thing in that kind, without, beſides, or beyond his <hi>Command.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Several other paſſages there are, beſides thoſe mentioned, of like character with them. <hi>If there be found among you — man or woman that hath wrought wickedneſs in the ſight of the Lord thy God, in tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing his Covenant, and hath gone and ſerved other gods, and worſhipped them, either the Sun, or Moon, or any of the Hoſt of Heaven, which I HAVE NOT COMMANDED,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.2, 3. <hi>Thy People which thou broughteſt out of Egypt, have corrupted themſelves: they are quickly turned aſide out of the way, WHICH I COMMANDED THEM, &amp;c.</hi> (Deut. 9.12.) implying, that in the Worſhip of God (of which he here ſpeaketh) <hi>to turn aſide out of the Way WHICH HE HATH COMMANDED,</hi> is to <hi>corrupt</hi> a man's ſelf [that is, to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, or prepare himſelf for ruine and deſtruction] unto what way ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he ſhall betake himſelf otherwiſe. <hi>And</hi> Nadab <hi>and</hi> Abihu, <hi>the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:103564:14"/>ſons of</hi> Aaron, <hi>took either of them his Cenſer, and put fire therein, and put Incenſe thereon, and offered ſtrange fire before the Lord, WHICH HE COMMANDED THEM NOT. And there went out Fire from the Lord, and devoured them, and they dyed before the Lord.</hi> Lev. 10.1, 2. In this high-provoking act of the Sons of <hi>Aaron,</hi> for which the ſevere jealouſie of God brake out immediatly upon them in a conſuming fire, there was no diſobedience to any Command, (I mean, unto any par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular or expreſs Command) of God: he had no where forbad them (at leaſt, explicitly or directly) to offer ordinary or common fire (which is termed <hi>ſtrange fire,</hi> becauſe the Commandment of God knew it not) in their Prieſtly Miniſtrations: nor is any diſobedience in this kind charged on them by the holy Ghoſt, nor ſo much as mentioned as any cauſe of that terrible execution, which was ſuddenly done by the imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate hand of God himſelf upon them: their only crime and guilt was, that <hi>they offered ſtrange fire before the Lord, WHICH HE COM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MANDED THEM NOT:</hi> they preſumed to worſhip God other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe than he had appointed, or commanded. The ſin of <hi>Uzzah</hi> in putting forth his hand to ſtay the Ark (for which he likewiſe ſuffered the ſame meaſure from the provoked jealouſie of God, being by him ſtruck dead in the place) was of like nature and conſideration. For neither did he therein tranſgreſs any expreſs Command of God: for he had no where commanded that none but the <hi>Levites</hi> ſhould touch or meddle with the Ark: only he had commanded that the <hi>Levites</hi> ſhould wait upon the Tabernacle with what appertained to it. So that the provocation in his ſin alſo, only was his intermedling with the holy things of God relating to his Worſhip, without his Command. And thus <hi>David,</hi> upon the ground that we maintain (namely that all Worſhip uncommanded, or unappointed by God, is unlawful and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing unto him; or, which is the ſame, that his order and appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment are requiſit to legitimate any Worſhip or holy Service) proved it to have been unlawful for any other to carry the Ark of God, but the <hi>Levites</hi> only. <hi>None</hi> (ſaith he, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 15.2.) <hi>ought to carry the Ark of God, but the Levites: for them hath the Lord choſen to carry the Ark of God, and to minister unto him for ever.</hi> It was unlawful for all other perſons, the <hi>Levites</hi> excepted, to carry the Ark of God; not becauſe he had prohibited them by the letter, or direct import, of any Law, to carry it, but becauſe he had not <hi>choſen,</hi> or appointed them, as he had the <hi>Levites.</hi> Again,</p>
            <p>Secondly, Of the ſame, or like import, with the texts already cited, are all thoſe alſo, in which God ſtigmatizeth the Worſhip which men performed unto him, with this character of his hatred, that it was of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:103564:15"/>their own chuſing, or deviſing, after the imagination of their own heart, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> In all ſuch places as theſe (which are not a few) he aſſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth unto himſelf the appointment of his own Worſhip, as belonging, prerogative-wiſe, unto himſelf, and wherein he will not indure any creature to have part and fellowſhip with him. For otherwiſe (as we reaſoned before) no Worſhip were reprovable ſimply upon this ſcore, that it is of mens own chuſing or deviſing. We ſhall not ſtand to ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue any of theſe places, as we did moſt of the other: the inference or reſult now mentioned from the general tenour of them all, is pregnant and convincing enough. And if it be an hateful brand upon any form of Worſhip to be of humane extraction, or to call any man, or any numbers of men, Father; how much more hateful and provoking in the fight of God muſt it needs be, to attempt to bind any ſuch ſpurious and baſe worſhip upon the generous and heaven-born conſciences of the ſons and daughters of God (or, indeed, upon the conſciences of any men) with the hard cords of Impriſonments, Confiſcations, Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments, or what other Cruelties <hi>Satan</hi> ſhall pleaſe to ſuggeſt unto men for the promoting of his worſhip and ſervice in the world, under the deluſive pretence of the Worſhip and Service of God? But places of the late mentioned character, are theſe (with their fellows) <hi>And it ſhall be unto you for a fringe, that ye may look upon it, and remember all the Commandments of the Lord, and do them: and that ye ſeek not AFTER YOUR OWN HEART, AND YOUR OWN EYES, after which ye uſe to go a whoring;</hi> Numb. 15.39. <hi>Take heed unto your ſelves that your heart be not deceived, and ye turn aſide, and ſerve other Gods, and worſhip them, and then the Lords Wrath be kindled againſt you, &amp;c.</hi> Deut. 11.16, 17. — <hi>And it cometh to paſs wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n he heareth the words of this Curſe, that he bleſſeth himſelf in his heart, ſaving, I ſhall have peace, though I walk IN THE IMAGINATION OF MINE OWN HEART;</hi> [That is, in ſuch a way of worſhipping God, as I conceive to be pleaſing to him, as appears by the mention of God's <hi>Jealouſie</hi> in the words following] <hi>to add drunkenneſs to thirſt. The Lord will not ſpare him, but the Anger of the Lord, and his Jealouſie ſhall ſmoke againſt that man, &amp;c.</hi> Deut. 29.19, 20. <hi>So he</hi> [Jeroboam] <hi>offered upon the Altar which he had made in Bethel the fifteenth day of the eighth month, even in the month VVHICH HE HAD DEVISED OF HIS OWN HEART, &amp;c.</hi> 1 King. 12.33. <hi>He that burneth Incenſe, is as if he bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed an Idol: yea, they have CHOSEN THEIR OWN VVAYES, and their ſoul delighteth in their abominations,</hi> Iſa. 66.3. From whence it is very obſervable (and maketh with an high hand for our preſent purpoſe) 1. That it is incident to men to <hi>chuſe wayes</hi> and methods of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:103564:15"/>their <hi>own [i. e.</hi> of their own deviſing] for the worſhipping of God, in ſtead of, and before, the wayes preſcribed by himſelf for that purpoſe. 2. That theſe <hi>ways</hi> of mens <hi>own</hi> deviſing and <hi>chooſing,</hi> are their <hi>abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations</hi> [that is, ways for which they muſt anſwer to God, as for things that are abominable in his ſight] or at leaſt, may be, yea, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times are ſuch. 3. (And laſtly) that notwithſtanding ſuch <hi>ways</hi> be their <hi>abominations,</hi> yet they are wont <hi>animitùs deperire,</hi> to love and <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in</hi> them with their whole ſoul; and to be enflamed with zeal over them (as the Scripture teſtifies in many places, and our own experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in the importune and bloody Promoters of the Service-Book, doth confirm) as if God himſelf loved and delighted in them as much as they.</p>
            <p>There are many more texts and paſſages of like notion with thoſe now cited, and which offer the right hand of fellowſhip unto the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, which hath been made good by them: but thoſe already menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, I judge abundantly ſufficient for the eviction of this Truth, That all worſhip of humane device, or contrivement, is of an unpleaſing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentment with God, and will be caſt as dung in the faces of thoſe, that ſhall offer it unto him, of how ſweet a ſavour ſoever it may be unto themſelves; and conſequently, that the appointment and command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his own Worſhip, is a darling prerogative unto him, the glory whereof he will not give unto another. The truth of this Doctrine runs clearly enough in other veines of Scripture, beſides thoſe in which we have ſeen it already; by the opening and arguing of which we might have more enterviews and appearances of it in ſomewhat differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſhapes. How ſtrict is the charge of God unto men, neither <hi>to add to, nor take from, the Word which he hath commanded them? that they turn not aſide from it, either to the right hand, or to the left?</hi> Deut. 4.2. &amp; 5.32. &amp; 12.32. &amp; 17.20. &amp; 28.14. <hi>Joſh.</hi> 1.7. <hi>Pro.</hi> 30.6. <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.18, 19. Doubtleſs they who turn their backs upon the Appointments and Commandments of God concerning his Worſhip, and will impoſe Apocryphal Forms and Models of Worſhip upon men, ſaying (in ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect) firſt to God himſelf, Except thou wilt be pleaſed with that wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip which we preſcribe and enjoyn, thou ſhalt not be worſhipped at all, as far as we have to do: and then unto Men, Unleſs you will worſhip God after our mode, and with the worſhip which we enjoyn you (be it good, or be it bad, true, or falſe) you ſhall not worſhip <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> at all, if we can help, or prevent it; ſuch m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n (I ſay) is theſe, do, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o a very broad ſence, both <hi>add unto, and diminiſh from, the Word <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> God hath commanded.</hi> I ſhall not need to interpre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>r pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of this aſſertion. And (indeed) for the conviction and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:103564:16"/>of thoſe, that are ſpiritually ingenious, and tremble to detain the truth in unrighteouſneſs, that which hath been already argued and pleaded from the Scriptures, I know cannot but ſuffice. But for thoſe that are <hi>contentious</hi> [or of cavilling ſpirits] and do not, will not, obey the Truth, if it toucheth the apple of their eye, and thwart their car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal intereſt, the Sun and a Sack-cloth, the Light of the Noon-day and the Darkneſs of the Mid-night, ſeven Demonſtrations from the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and ſeven Stories out of the Golden Legion, are much alike. Yet let us (in a few words) further weigh and conſider that ingenuous acknowledgment of the great Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> that he <hi>had not a dominion over their Faith,</hi> 2 Cor. 1.24. To have <hi>dominion over</hi> a mans <hi>Faith,</hi> requireth a lawful Authority to impoſe any thing upon him to be believed, which the Impo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er pleaſeth, or judgeth meet, upon the account of his own judgement and will, and under what pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty he pleaſeth: and again, to prohibit him the believing any thing upon the like tearms. Now then evident it is, that neither <hi>Paul,</hi> nor <hi>Cephas,</hi> nor <hi>Principalities,</hi> nor <hi>Powers,</hi> nor <hi>Cherubims,</hi> nor <hi>Seraphims,</hi> nor all the Angels in Heaven, have any <hi>dominion over the Faith</hi> of men, but only He, whoſe judgment is univerſally, and in all things, infallible, and his will in like manner impeccable. Eſpecially the <hi>Dominion</hi> we ſpeak of, is not competent unto, cannot reaſonably be imagined to be veſted in ſuch a creature, that <hi>knoweth but in part,</hi> that <hi>ſeeth darkly,</hi> and <hi>through a glaſs</hi> only, and beſides, is <hi>ſold under ſin,</hi> and <hi>in,</hi> or with, <hi>his fleſh, ſerveth the Law of ſin:</hi> all which our Apoſtle acknowledgeth of himſelf; and that which concerneth imperfection of knowledge, he affirmeth of all men without exception even of the moſt enlightned <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.9, 12. And if ſo great an Apoſtle, who was ſo high in favour with God, as to be <hi>taken up into the third Heaven,</hi> where he heard words <hi>that were unſpeakable,</hi> and <hi>which it was not lawful</hi> [or, poſſible: theſe were the ſame with <hi>Paul] for a man to utter;</hi> and who (doubtleſs) knew more of the mind of God, and of Chriſt, than all the world beſides; and beyond all this, was ſo mightily ſubdued under the Truth, that (as he profeſſeth) he <hi>could do nothing againſt it, but</hi> [do, and ſuffer all things] <hi>for it;</hi> yea, and was ſo effectually mortified unto the world, that he <hi>could moſt gladly ſpend and be ſpent,</hi> for the ſouls of men; if (I ſay) an Apoſtle thus highly accompliſhed above all his fellows, and in the largeſt capacity amongſt ten thouſand, to be made a Lord over the Faith of men, yet was not by God judged meet for ſuch an inveſtiture (himſelf declaring, and profeſſing as much, as we heard) how intollerable is it in men, who, being compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with <hi>Paul,</hi> ſcarce hold the proportion of the ſnuff of a Candle to
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:103564:16"/>the Sun, to claim, and exerciſe that moſt high and ſacred <hi>Dominion</hi> we ſpeak of, as if it were veſted by God in them? Or do they any whit leſs than claim &amp; exerciſe it, who under ſore mulcts and penalties, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe a neceſſity upon men to believe, ſubſcribe unto, and teach what conceits, opinions, and tenets they pleaſe, in things appertaining to God, and withall, to renounce and abjure all ſuch opinions and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions which pleaſe them not? Or do not they broadly uſurp the <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion</hi> we ſpeak of, who command men at the peril of their Eſtates, Livelyhoods, Liberties, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to believe that ſuch or ſuch a Form of divine Worſhip, which pleaſeth them, pleaſeth God alſo; yea, and that it pleaſeth him better than any other Form, yea, than any other Worſhip whatſoever, which they are capable of performing, or exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibiting unto him? Or do they thus command men to uſe their Form of Worſhip, whether they, whom they command, believe it to be pleaſing unto God or no? If this be the ſence of their command, it is yet more imperiouſly impious, and horridly prophane. Therefore in commanding them to uſe it, they implicitely, yet next to explicitly, command them to believe it to be lawful and good. Nay if they right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly underſtood the nature and import of that command of theirs we ſpeak of, they do not only command thoſe, on whom they impoſe it, to believe that the Form of Worſhip enjoyned them, is ſimply lawful, but that it is better and more acceptable unto God, not only than any other ſet Form of Worſhip they can uſe, but then any other Worſhip, kind or manner of Worſhip whatſoever, of which they are capable. For he that ſhall uſe any ſet Form of Worſhip, without ſuch a belief as this (I mean, without being perſwaded in his ſoul, that he cannot Worſhip God better in any other way, or by any other Form) expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth himſelf to the curſe denounced, <hi>Mal.</hi> 1.14. <hi>Curſed be the Deceiver, that hath a male in his flock, and voweth, and ſacrificeth unto the Lord a corrupt thing. [debile,</hi> a weak thing, as the Latine rendreth; which <hi>Grotius</hi> explains, by <hi>vitioſum, aut foemininum,</hi> that which is faulty, or feminine] <hi>For I am a great King, ſaith the Lord of Hoſts, and my Name is dreadfull among the Heathen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What hath been demonſtrated from the Scriptures concerning the Prerogative of God touching his own Worſhip, is not obſcurely taught by the Light of Nature it ſelf, and by the Principles of Reaſon; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially if we ſhall allow them now and then a little aſſiſtance and relief from the Scriptures. For,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Light of Nature carrieth us up to the Truth we contend for, by theſe gradations or ſteps. 1. It teacheth us that God is to be worſhipped by his creature, Man. 2. That he is to be worſhipped with
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:103564:17"/>ſuch Worſhip, which is moſt agreeable unto the excellency of his Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and Divine Being, and which is moſt honourable for him to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive. 3. It teacheth us further; That that Worſhip which is moſt agreeable unto his Nature, and moſt honourable for him to receive, is to be dictated and preſcribed by the moſt perfect knowledge of his Nature and Being, that is to be found. For he that is in any degree ignorant of theſe, cannot direct a Worſhip, or manner of Worſhip, agreeable to Him, or to his Nature, as he may, who perfectly know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Him, and comprehendeth all his Perfections. 4. The ſame Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er likewiſe informeth us, That every creature is finite, and partaketh of Entity and Being but by meaſure, and that God the Creator of all things, is Infinite, and He only. 5. From the ſame hand, we are clearly inſtructed yet further, That the moſt perfect of Creatures, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Finite, is not able, no not by the greateſt enlargement of its en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowments or abilities from God, to know perfectly, or to comprehend the Infinite Perfection of the Divine Being: but that God, by the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of his Infinity, is able fully to comprehend it, yea, that he doth actually thus comprehend it. By this ſeries, or chain of natural Maxims, we are advanced unto the ground of our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent conteſt; namely, That God himſelf is only competent to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe and dictate his own Worſhip, all Creatures being ſtrangers, in compariſon of himſelf, to his moſt tranſcendent Excellency and Being, and conſequently, incompetent to contrive or frame a Worſhip ſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able unto him; and much more to impoſe (ſome, upon others) and this with extream rigour, any Form of Worſhip of their own deviſing, this (being interpreted by the premiſes) being a Worſhip unſuitable to the Nature of God, and ſo unacceptable unto him. Again,</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Light of Nature enlighteneth our Judgments with this Truth, That the Worſhip, manner or kind of Worſhip, which is agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the Nature of God, and ſo accepted with him, is but one and the ſame Worſhip, or kind of Worſhip, as his Nature is but one and the ſame. So that though he commandeth <hi>every Kindred, and Tongue, and People, and Nation under Heaven,</hi> to worſhip him, yet the Worſhip which he requireth of them all, is for manner, and kind, but one and the ſame, nor diverſified in any ſuch reſpect as theſe, by any exigency of circumſtance, one, or more, whatſoever. What this one kind of Worſhip is, which we affirm God requireth of all, ſhall be ſhewed in due place, and this ere long. In the mean time proceed we with our Argument in hand. If God requireth one and the ſame kind of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of all People and Nations, doubtleſs he hath not inveſted any of theſe Nations, much leſs the Rulers or Governours of any of theſe
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:103564:17"/>Nations, with any authority, or right of power to worſhip him, with what kind, or form of Worſhip they pleaſe. Much leſs hath he given authorrity to any one part, or party, in any of theſe Nations, to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe upon all the reſt in their Nation, contrary to their Judgments and Conſciences, what manner, form, or kind of Worſhip they fancy to be beſt pleaſing unto him. Or if he hath given any ſuch authority as this unto the ruling or prevailing party, in any one of theſe Nations, queſtionleſs he hath given the like, or the ſame, unto the like party or parties in them all: for there is no competent Reaſon aſſignable, why any difference ſhould be made between them in this caſe. If then the Rulers and Governours of all Nations under Heaven, have an equal right of Power derived unto them from God, to impoſe upon the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple under them, what Worſhip ſeemeth good in their eyes, Idolatrous Princes ſhall have as much, and as lawful authority to impoſe any Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous Worſhip upon thoſe under them, as thoſe that know God, and are truly religious, have to impoſe a better Worſhip upon thoſe that are ſubject unto them. For there is little queſtion to be made, but that in the eyes of an Idolatrous Prince, an Idolatrous Worſhip will ſeem as good (or better) as the trueſt Worſhip doth in the eyes of a Prince truly <hi>Chriſtian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If it be ſaid, A Prince impoſing an Idolatrous Worſhip, abuſeth his Authority: but this ought not to be pleaded in Bar to the regular and due exerciſe of the like Authority, by another Prince. I anſwer,</p>
            <p n="1">1. If he hath Authority from God to impoſe ſuch a VVorſhip, which he judgeth to be good, and pleaſing unto God, he doth not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe this Authority by acting according to the tenor and purport of it, which he doth when he impoſeth only ſuch a Worſhip, which he really judgeth to be good, however he be miſtaken in his judgement in the caſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. A Prince profeſſing <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Religion, abuſeth his Authority as much (or rather more) when he impoſeth upon his Subjects, being <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> any falſe VVorſhip, or ſuch which is diſpleaſing unto God. And however, when he adventures to impoſe any VVorſhip at all, not being infallible, he runs a double hazard of abuſing his Authority. For firſt, he may miſtake the VVorſhip, which he impoſeth, ſuppoſing it to be legitimate, and pleaſing unto God, when (indeed) it is ſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, and an abhorring to his ſoul. Men of great learning and parts, and ſtudied in the Scriptures far above the ordinary rate of Princes, have, with great confidence, built errours and miſtakes as great and dangerous as that, upon miſpriſions of Scriptuere. Secondly, The Prince we ſpeak of, runneth yet a greater hazard of abuſing his Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity in impoſing any VVorſhip at all, becauſe he cannot know, no nor
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:103564:18"/>yet conjecture upon any probable or competent grounds, that it is pleaſing unto God, that he ſhould impoſe any thing in this kind. Yea, it is ſcarce any queſtion at all, but that to compell men by penal threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings and executions, to ſubmit to any form or kind of Worſhip, be it never ſo plauſible, is an abuſe of any created Authority whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever.</p>
            <p>Beſides all this; If God impoſeth one and the ſame Worſhip, or kind of Worſhip, upon all Nations under Heaven (which is a ſuppoſition of unqueſtionable Truth, as was lately hinted with the ground of it) he ſhould act contrary to his own Deſign or Command in this behalf, in caſe he ſhould give Authority to the Rulers of theſe Nations, or to any party in them (reſpectively) to ſet up or impoſe what forms or kinds of Worſhip they ſhould apprehend and judge to be moſt fitting to be impoſed or ſet up. The grant of ſuch Authority would be a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect courſe to fill the world with as many forms and ſhapes, or kinds of Worſhip, as there are Nations in it, and Rulers over them; yea, and all that enormous variety of ſuperſtitious, idolatrous and falſe Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, which are, or have been impoſed, countenanced, practiſed in the greateſt part of theſe Nations, and which hath been hitherto charged by <hi>Chriſtians</hi> generally upon the Devil, and his ſubtilty and bloody ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice againſt the precions Souls of men, muſt, upon a ſuppoſal of ſuch a grant from God to the Rulers of theſe Nations, as that mentioned, be rather reſolved into God. This Argument might be further impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, but that we make haſte. Therefore</p>
            <p n="3">3. Neither doth it in the Eye of Reaſon, look like one of the ways of God, to leave ſome Mens Conſciences free, and at liberry, to ſerve and worſhip him according to the beſt of their underſtandings, and of that light of Knowledge which he hath given them; and yet withal, to ſubject and enſlave the Conſciences of others unto the humours, wills, and fancies of men, in theſe moſt high and ſacred concernments. Leaſt of all ſeemeth it to have any affinity with his Righteouſneſs, Wiſdom and Impartialneſs, viſible enough in all his other Adminiſtrations, to ſubject the Conſciences of ſuch men who have known the Scriptures from their youth, and have ſpent all their days, it may be many years, in a conſciencious and diligent ſtudy and ſearch of them; and withal, are known to be men of Integrity, of ſignal Piety, of great Knowledge in the things of God, of a vertuous and Chriſtian Converſation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to ſubject (I ſay) the Conſciences of great numbers of ſuch Perſons as theſe, in matters appertaining to the Worſhip of God, unto the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, dictates, and conceits of a few men, who have wholly (in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner) addicted themſelves either to other ſtudies, or to ſecular employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:103564:18"/>(if not to ways and practiſes more alienating from God then theſe) and ſo muſt needs be (comparatively at leaſt) ſtrangers to the Scriptures, and unacquainted with the mind of God here, is a device or contrivance of quite another Spirit then that which breatheth in all the Councils, Diſpenſations, and Adminiſtrations of God. He did not make the leſſer but the <hi>greater Light to rule the Day:</hi> though he gave a great preheminence in ſtrength unto the Lion and the Unicorn, above Man, yet did he not judge it meet to give unto either of them, <hi>Dominion over the Works of his Hands,</hi> or <hi>to put all things under their feet:</hi> His Wiſdom and Goodneſs inveſted his Creature <hi>Man,</hi> (having furniſhed him with knowledge and underſtanding) with this honour and dignity. Neither did he intend or make the Body to be the light of the Eye, but the Eye to be the light of the Body, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.22. Nor did he order or intend the dim-ſighted World for a light unto the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, nor the unſavoury Earth to be as Salt to ſeaſon them; but the Apoſtles to be the light of the one, and the Salt of the other, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.13, 14. They who are called to places of Magiſtracy, or Rule, and to the honour of Law-making, in any State, or Community of Men, look upon themſelves as being at full liberty to abrogate or repeal any Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment, or Law, made by their Predeceſſors for the worſhipping of God in any external way or form of Worſhip; and conſequently, as being at liberty themſelves to worſhip God for the future either with a ſet Form, or without, as in their Conſciences they ſhall judge it beſt pleaſing unto God. Yea, they claim a liberty, though they ſhall make a penal Law to conſtrain the generality of their People to ſuch or ſuch a ſtinted Form in the Worſhip of God, yet to grant unto what perſons they pleaſe, whether of themſelves or others, an exemption from this Law. Now this is that which I affirm, as the clear dictate of Reaſon, That God hath left the Conſciences of all men equally bound, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually free, in the matter of his Worſhip; and that, as he hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded and bound Kings and Princes, and Law-makers themſelves, as well as meaner men, to worſhip and ſerve him with the beſt of their underſtandings; ſo hath he exempted even the meaneſt ſort of men, as well as Kings and Princes themſelves, from all compulſion, whether by Laws, or otherwiſe, to worſhip or ſerve him upon any other, I mean upon any lower, meaner, or worſe terms.</p>
            <p n="4">4, (And laſtly, at preſent) Reaſon it ſelf prompteth us with this <hi>Dilemma</hi> alſo in the caſe: Either God hath himſelf preſcribed unto men how, or with what kind of Worſhip he will be worſhipped; or elſe he hath done nothing in this kind, but left men at liberty to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip ſo or ſo, as their own Judgements and Conſciences ſhall teach
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:103564:19"/>and direct them: If this latter be affirmed, (which yet is not ſo <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian</hi> to affirm) then whoſoever ſhall impoſe a particular form of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip upon men, oppoſeth the Counſel and Deſign of God about his Worſhip, which (according to the ſuppoſition we now argue) is to be worſhipped as every mans own Judgement and Conſcience, not other mens, ſhall teach and direct him. If the former horn of the <hi>Dilem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma</hi> be taken hold of, and acknowledgement be made, that God hath himſelf preſcribed and commanded his own Worſhip, the terms and manner of it, (which I preſume will be the ſober <hi>Chriſtians</hi> choice) then for men to impoſe any other, any form of Worſhip of their own or other mens deviſing, muſt needs be preſumption in the higheſt. For what is this but to ſet their <hi>threſholds</hi> by Gods <hi>threſhold,</hi> and their <hi>poſts</hi> by his <hi>poſts? Ezek.</hi> 43.8. yea, to affront the Wiſdom of God with their wiſdom, his Authority with theirs; and as much as in them lieth, by their Commandments to <hi>make the Commandments of God of none ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If it be replied and ſaid, That though it be granted, that God hath preſcribed and commanded his own Worſhip, yet this is to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood onely of the matter or ſubſtance of it in general (together with the inward manner of performing it) not that he hath preſcribed any particular form of words, wherein or wherewith he would have men con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly to worſhip him. If this were ſo, they ſhould ſin as much againſt his Commandment of Worſhip, who worſhip him in or with conceived Prayer, as they who preſcribe forms of Prayers unto others; inaſmuch as no conceived <hi>Prayer</hi> is any whit more preſcribed or commanded by <hi>God,</hi> then a form of Prayer impoſed; and as for the matter of either, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived Prayer is much more likely to be delinquent, then the other. For that which hath been deliberately compoſed and digeſted by many, and theſe equal (or rather much ſuperiour) in Piety and parts of Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, is like to have more ſpiritual weight and worth in it, and be more acceptable unto God, then any thing conceived, and uttered <hi>ex tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore,</hi> and without premeditation, by a ſingle perſon, and he (it may be) leſs conſiderable in both. To all this, I anſwer:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Conceived Prayer, is, for the nature and kind of it, that very Worſhip (at leaſt, as far as Worſhip conſiſts in Prayer; for there may be other VVorſhip, or parts of VVorſhip, then that which is exhibited or performed unto God in Prayer) which he preſcribeth and command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, at leaſt unto thoſe that are, or by the uſe of means, may be, ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of it, as all Miniſters of the Goſpel generally are preſumed to be. By <hi>conceived Prayer,</hi> I do not mean onely that kind of Prayer which is conceived and uttered <hi>ex tempore,</hi> without ſtudy or premedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:103564:19"/>or which is never uſed but once by him that uttereth it; but that likewiſe which is or hath been conceived, framed, and digeſted by him that uttereth it, although with deliberation and ſtudy, and hath been frequently at ſeveral times, eſpecially if with any occaſional va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riations, uſed by him. In the Scriptures, eſpecially in the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (where the light ſhines cleareſt for the diſcovery of the mind of God in all points concerning Prayer and VVorſhip) we hardly find the ſame prayer uſed the ſecond time by the ſame perſon. For though Chriſt be ſaid to have <hi>prayed the ſame words</hi> a ſecond and a third time, yet by comparing <hi>Mat.</hi> 20.39. with <hi>v.</hi> 42. <hi>&amp;</hi> 44. and <hi>Mark</hi> 14. <hi>v.</hi> 35. with 36. it appears that it is to be underſtood of the <hi>ſame words</hi> in ſenſe, matter, and import, or in effect; not the ſame in ſound, letters, or ſyllables, (words being put for matters or things frequently in the Scriptures:) yea, all the Prayers here recorded to have been made, either by Chriſt himſelf, or by his Apoſtles, or other holy perſons, and which found acceptance which God, were framed by them with a ſpecial and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular reference unto the preſent occaſions that were before them (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectively) and therefore cannot but be judged to have been <hi>conceived Prayers</hi> (in the ſtricteſt ſence of the VVords) yea, all the Exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons unto the heavenly Exerciſe and Duty of Prayer, delivered either by Chriſt or his Apoſtles, intended onely that kind of Prayer, which we commonly call conceived Prayer, which the Saints were to conceive and indite by the help of the Spirit of God, (<hi>Rom.</hi> 8.27.) which they who believed did receive, <hi>John</hi> 7.39. <hi>Act.</hi> 5.32. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.5. &amp; 8.14, 15, 16. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.5. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.2. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.13. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.8. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.27. &amp; 3.24. &amp; 4.13. which places, (at leaſt the moſt of them) cannot be underſtood either of the miraculous Gift of the Holy Ghoſt, or of the giving of him to the Apoſtles onely, and ſome particular Chriſtians with them. This will be evident unto thoſe that ſhall pleaſe to take a little pains to peruſe and ponder them. Several others of like import might be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded unto them. Beſides, that the ſaid Exhortations unto <hi>Prayer,</hi> were meant of conceived Prayer, and not of praying by any ſtinted form impoſed, at leaſt by any Civil Authority, leaſt of all impoſed with threatnings of Civil Mulcts and Penalties; are all of them Truths ſo full of their own Light, that to levy any further proof of them, would be but as the lighting up of a Candle to help men to ſee the Light of the Sun. Books, and forms of Prayer of humane contrivance and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, would (we may very reaſonably preſume) have been in the days of thoſe Exhortations, and for many days after them, as prodigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and aſtoniſhing unto Chriſtians, as the turning of the Sun into dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and the Moon into blood.</p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:103564:20"/>
            <p n="2">2dly. Whereas it was pleaded, That a Prayer framed by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>current abilities and gifts of ſeveral pious and learned men, and this upon mature conſideration, muſt needs in Reaſon be a more effectual Prayer, and better accepted with God, than a Prayer conceived and brought forth on the ſudden by a particular man, and he (many times) of no great parts or learning neither. I anſwer,</p>
            <p n="1">1. This plea of compariſon between prayer and prayer, (be it ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted) doth not make the face of our <hi>Common-Prayer-Book</hi> to ſhine at all. For who can make <hi>affidavit</hi> that the prayers here are the iſſue of the abilities or gifts, I do not ſay of <hi>many,</hi> but of <hi>any</hi> pious or learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed man? There is little queſtion to be made, but that in <hi>Latine</hi> it firſt ſaw the light of the Sun, when the groſs darkneſs of Popery was ſpread over the face of the Earth (in theſe parts of the world) and when the mother of it (the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> I mean) was guilty but of little <hi>Learning</hi> and leſs <hi>Piety.</hi> It is likeſt to have been the officious elucu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bration of ſome ſuperſtitious Monk or Friar, calculated by the beſt of his art and skill, for the meridian of the devotions of that Apoſtate Church in his dayes. As for thoſe worthy and good men in King <hi>Edward</hi>'s dayes, who with a much better intent than event, took pains to fetch it out of <hi>Latine</hi> into <hi>Engliſh,</hi> making account that they had left all the dregs and excrementitious matter behind them, we were their compurgators formerly that they were not the Authors or Compilers of this unhappy Book, nor guilty of the folly committed in the begetting of it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The goodneſs or excellency of a Prayer for matter, phraſe and ſtructure, is rather an argument why it ſhould be left free for men to uſe, when, and as far as they ſee cauſe, than why it ſhould be impoſed. Becauſe, 1. The impoſition of it is rather matter of prejudice, and diſparagement unto it, than otherwiſe; Impoſers ſeldom dealing in ſuch commodities which are choice, ſound and good, but very fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently in thoſe which are faulty, and baſe. 2. The impoſition of it alters the property of the goodneſs of it, &amp; makes it to become an Idol (as we formerly argued the caſe) and conſequently expoſeth it to the jealouſie and high diſpleaſure of God, and hereby to an utter abolition and ruine (as we concluded likewiſe from the Scriptures) And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, as it is better, of the two, to make an Idol of Dirt or Clay, or ſome ſuch vile material, than of Silver, or Gold, or of any thing of va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue, becauſe it is better that that which is of little worth ſhould pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh and be loſt, than that which is more precious and uſeful: ſo is it, in this reſpect at leaſt, more to be wiſhed, that ſuch prayers, and ſuch forms of Divine Service (ſo called) which are corrupt, and not fit to
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:103564:20"/>be uſed by any good <hi>Chriſtian</hi> upon any terms, ſhould be impoſed, than thoſe which are more commendable, and might be ſome wayes ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable and helpful to the piety and devotions of good people other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe. 3. (and laſtly, for this) As <hi>Samuel</hi> in reproving <hi>Saul,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth; <hi>Hath the Lord as great delight in burnt offerings and Sacrifices, as in obeying the voice of the Lord? Behold, to obey is letter than jacrifice, and to hearken, than the fat of Lambs;</hi> 1 Sam. 15.22. So is a Prayer conceived and brought forth in obedience unto the Counſel and Will of God, though it be not ſo eloquent, nor the matter of it ſo choice, nor the method or frame of it ſo exact, of better acceptance with God, than a Prayer read out of a Book, whether without or contrary unto the Command of God; (for it hath been proved from the Scriptures, that theſe two, in the caſe of Worſhip, are but of one and the ſame conſideration) yea, though this prayer, for matter, language and frame, ſhould be of as happy a calculation, as the piety and parts of men in their greateſt perfection, are able to advance. But,</p>
            <p n="3">3. (And laſtly) To the reaſon or ground of the Plea mentioned, I anſwer; That in caſe a great number of men (ſuppoſing them both pious and learned) ſhould conveen and take what time they pleaſe, to compoſe a Prayer, with an intent to impoſe it, or with a deſire that it ſhould be impoſed upon their <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Brethren, it is not ſo proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble (as is pleaded and pretended) that the Prayer framed by them upon ſuch terms ſhould have any ſpiritual or real worth in it, or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailingneſs with God, above the prayer conceived and uttered with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out premeditation (I mean, in reference unto this particular prayer, more than unto others) by a perſon in gifts and parts of learning, inferiour to them, only ſuppoſing him to be a good man, and fearing God. For they who are imployed about making Prayers to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed upon <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> are about <hi>Satans</hi> work, making Iron yokes and ſnares for the Sons and Daughters of God: and certain it is that God takes no pleaſure to be aſſiſting unto men, no not unto his own, in the way of ſuch an occupation: and where God with his bleſſing is abſent, no undertakeing, eſpecially no ſpiritual undertakeing, is like greatly to proſper in the hands of men, though never ſo well accompliſhed for their work. Whereas he that conſcientiouſly addreſleth himſelf un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God by prayer, and is careful to pray according to his Will, doth the work of God; and conſequently, may (as it were) of courſe expect the aſſiſting preſence of God with him in his way, which many times acteth men above their line and ſphere; and at no time, when it is vouchſafed, ſuffereth them ſo to miſcarry, as to loſe their acceptance with God.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:103564:21"/>
            <p>And thus we ſee that all Worſhip, formed, preſcribed, and impoſed by men, is heterogeneal and ſpurious, and which the Scriptures, yet and all principles of ſound reaſon diſdain to give the right hand of fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip unto.</p>
            <p>What will our zealous and ſevere Promoters of the <hi>Common-Prayer-Book-Worſhip,</hi> ſay to theſe things? If God be againſt them in their Cauſe, who or what can be with them (to any purpoſe?) The colours wherewith they commonly paint the face of it, to give it the beſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion it will take, are very waſhy, faint, and fading: So that what <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſpake in a caſe that would not ſo well bear it, I may, upon a try'd account, ſay concerning the Cauſe that now hath been argued: <hi>Scio contra hanc, quam defendimus, ſententiam, neminem niſi errando diſputare poſſe:</hi> I know that no man can diſpute againſt the opinion we maintain, but by erring [from the Truth.] The common Pleas for the lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the uſe of ſtinted Forms of Prayer, I paſs over, onely with theſe two <hi>Memorandums:</hi> 1. That the moſt ſubſtantial proof of the meer lawfulneſs of them, will not reach the juſtification of the uſe of them by any Perſon (much leſs will it juſtifie the penal impoſition of them:) the reaſon is, becauſe there is nothing done by any perſon in or about the Worſhip or Service of God, but is either more then law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful (as either expedient or neceſſary) or elſe unlawful. That which is expedient, or fitting to be done in the caſe we ſpeak of, is (to a degree at leaſt, or in a ſenſe) neceſſary; and ſo more then ſimply or meerly lawful: that which is not expedient, or not fitting to be done, is (que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtionleſs) if it be done, unlawful. Therefore they that undertake to prove the lawfulneſs of ſet Forms of Prayer, and no more, though they ſhould make good their enterprize, yet would they not hereby lay a ſufficient Foundation for any perſon actually to uſe them. The reaſon hereof may be touched before we conclude. Yea, it is as true of all deliberate and moral actions, that the lawfulneſs of them ſimply and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>definitely conſidered, doth not prove it to be abſolutely or univerſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly lawful for any man to do them; but onely under and with appropri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate and due circumſtances. Therefore (to put in this by the way) to juſtifie the lawfulneſs of the uſe of things indifferent in the Worſhip of God, meerly upon this ground, that they are indifferent in themſelves, and out of the VVorſhip of God, and ſo lawful, is ſufficiently ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous and childiſh: but to juſtifie this uſe of them againſt the grain of ſo many material and weighty circumſtances as riſe up againſt it, and with greateſt importunity diſſwade from it (eſpecially in this Nation) is little leſs then bidding a defiance to all Chriſtian Ingenuity, and a diſclaiming of all reſpects both to God and Man. 2. That the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:103564:21"/>of ſtinted Liturgies, or ſet Forms of Prayer, though never ſo demonſtratively proved, would be no ſalve to heal the ſore (or rather the many ſores) of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Service-Book: Some account hereof was given towards the beginning.</p>
            <p>The bent of the preſent diſcourſe hath ſtood chiefly againſt the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of Forms for the Worſhip of God, and partly againſt a ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to the uſe of them upon the account of ſuch impoſition. Let us now taſte the ſpirit of thoſe Arguments, or of ſome of the chief of them, by which the Lords and Maſters of theſe impoſitions are wont to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to make that which is crooked, ſtreight. They that of old pleaded for Idols, had (it ſeems) their <hi>ſtrong Reaſons</hi> (ſuch as they thought <hi>ſtrong</hi>) to maintain the Cauſe of their Clients. <hi>Produce your Cauſe, ſaith the Lord: bring forth your ſtrong Reaſons,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 41.21. And men of impoſing Principles, appear upon all occaſions, to be as confident as they were, who went before them in the way of their ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, <hi>binding heavy burthens, and grievous to be born, and laying them on mens ſhoulders,</hi> (as our Saviour chargeth the <hi>Scribes and Phariſees</hi> to have done in his dayes, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.4.) Some of theſe, in the height of their confidence, that whoever were ignorant, they were men of knowledge, and of profound and ſharp underſtandings, demanded of <hi>Chriſt</hi> (in the name, as it ſeems, of all their fellows) not with a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle indignation, <hi>Are we blind alſo?</hi> (<hi>John</hi> 9.40.) being jealous that he had ſorely diſparaged them, in binding them up in the ſame bandle with the ignorant world. But as highly conceited as they were of their knowledge and wiſdom, the Lord <hi>Chriſt,</hi> dealing plainly with them, in reproving them, calleth them <hi>fools,</hi> and <hi>blind guides,</hi> over and over, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.16, 17, 19. And (if it be lawful to call a Spade a Spade) the great Proctors of the <hi>Impoſitions</hi> we ſpeak of (reſerving unto them all the honour due unto their learning and parts, otherwiſe) when they riſe up in their might to plead for theſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>profeſſing themſelves to be wiſe</hi> [and to carry all clear before them] <hi>they become fools</hi> [and leave their Cauſe quite behind them] <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.22. yea in theſe Diſputes they ſeem ſcarce men, or to have <hi>put away child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh things.</hi> A late great <hi>Hyperaſpiſtes</hi> of <hi>Liturgical</hi> devotions, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all (as you may preſume) of all their appurtenances, and pre-requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſites, as 1. <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> (the Pillar, and Ground-work of all) 2. Of <hi>Penal Impoſitions</hi> of them, without which they would not be ſuffered to live, where the light of true <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> ſhineth. 3. Of ſubjection to the Com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ands of Authority, whether with ſcruple, or without, a Principle that will enable men to ſwallow them, though they be Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mels (with ſeverall other Hierarchical notions, and devices, neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:103564:22"/>for the ſupporting of that frame) this Champion (I ſay) of <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgies,</hi> who alloweth us not the liberty of calling him by his Name, yet inſulteth with this Argument, over all that oppoſeth him in his way.
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>That Service of God which is conſonant to holy Scripture, is lawful:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The Service of God performed by a Preſcribed Liturgie, is conſonant to holy Scripture.</hi> Ergo.</l>
               </q> This Syllogiſm, were it narrowly ſifted, how much droſs would be found in it! Both Propoſitions being ambiguous, and ſpeaking nothing di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly, the whole Argument amounts to nothing, unleſs it be a ſnare to catch the unwary and leſs conſiderate. For the Philoſophers Rule is true: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Not to ſignifie one thing</hi> [diſtinctly, and with determination] <hi>is to ſignifie nothing.</hi> Let us touch a particular or two, in either Propoſition. In the <hi>Major,</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The word <hi>lawful,</hi> ſignifieth both that which is <hi>lawful</hi> ſimply, or in the nature of it, and circumſtances ſecluded, or that which is <hi>lawful</hi> in the practique of it, where circumſtances alwayes have to do, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times render that unlawful in the doing, or to be done, which in the nature of it, was <hi>lawful</hi> enough, and might have been <hi>lawful</hi> alſo in the Practiſe. We ſhall not need to give Inſtance: the Notion is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon and clear. So then, this Propoſition, <hi>That Service of God which is conſonant to the holy Scripture, is lawful,</hi> may be true in the former ſence of the word <hi>lawful,</hi> and yet falſe in the latter (which yet, queſtion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, is the ſence of the Syllogizer: for he argues for the lawfulneſs of the uſe or practiſe of the <hi>Service</hi> he ſpeaks) For that <hi>Service of God,</hi> which is really, truly, and in it ſelf <hi>conſonant to holy Scripture,</hi> may be diſtonant and contrary hereunto in the judgment and conſcience of thoſe on whom it is impoſed, and ſo the uſe of it, during this ſtate of their judgment, unlawful unto them. There are other circumſtances, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides this now mentioned, which may render even ſuch a <hi>Service of God as is conſonant to holy Scripture,</hi> unlawful to be practiſed. But we ſhal leave theſe at preſent, to exerciſe the Thinking faculty of the Diſputer. On<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly I deſire leave to put this Queſtion to him at this turn: Whether, it being ſuppoſed, that the <hi>Service of God,</hi> contained in the Liturgy of <hi>Baſil, Gregory,</hi> or any of thoſe now uſed in many of the Reformed Churches, is as <hi>conſonant to the holy Scripture,</hi> as that ſet forth in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Service-Book, is notwithſtanding <hi>lawful</hi> to be uſed by the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of this Nation? If not (for I preſume he will appear on the denying hand) then is there ſome-what more than a <hi>conſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ancy to holy Scripture,</hi> required to make the <hi>Service of God LAWFUL</hi> in the practique of it, and this, in the judgement of this <hi>Argumentator,</hi> muſt
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:103564:22"/>be the Command of that Authority, within the Juriſdiction of which it is performed. A worthy Poſition! the Conſequences whereof I wiſh he would ſeriouſly and unpartially compute at his leiſure. But,</p>
            <p n="2">2. Neither is this expreſſion, or phraſe, <hi>conſonant to the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> free from ambiguity in the ſenſe &amp; meaning of it, as the Epiſcopal dialect hath enlarged its ſignification. For they who are wont to plead for an impoſition of Liturgies and Ceremonies, call that which is not contrary to the expreſs letter of ſome particular prohibition or other, in the Scripture, <hi>conſonant to the Scripture,</hi> as well as that which is agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to ſome expreſs command there. Now then, if by <hi>conſonant to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scripture,</hi> he only means, not repugnant, or not contrary, to ſome expreſs prohibition in <hi>holy Scripture,</hi> his Propoſition is broadly repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant unto the Truth. For it hath been formerly proved from the <hi>holy Scripture,</hi> that in matter of Worſhip, not to be commanded, and to be prohibited, are of a like conſideration before God. Therefore <hi>that Service of God,</hi> which is <hi>conſonant to the holy Scripture</hi> only in that Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcopally-appropriate ſence of the phraſe, is not upon ſuch an account, <hi>lawful.</hi> And that this is, or muſt be his ſenſe of the ſaid phraſe, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, is evident from hence, becauſe otherwiſe his Argument would have nothing to do with his Cauſe. For certain it is, That <hi>preſcribed Liturgies,</hi> or, <hi>the Service of God performed by them,</hi> are not <hi>conſonant to holy Scripture</hi> in the other ſence of the phraſe; that is, are neither formally, or expreſly, nor yet virtually, or conſequentially command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed there. Thus we ſee the <hi>Major</hi> Propoſition of the <hi>Grand Sylegiſm</hi> in the <hi>Grand Debate,</hi> is homonymous, captious, and fallacious: which is enough to lay the credit of the Argument managed in it, in the duſt. Yet neither is the <hi>Minor</hi> better conditioned, if not worſe. For,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Here we have our double-tongu'd expreſſion again, <hi>Conſonant to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scripture.</hi> So that here is lying in wait alſo for thoſe that do not look well about them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Theſe words, <hi>a Preſcribed Liturgy,</hi> are as double-minded, as thoſe other. For they may ſignifie, either a <hi>Liturgie</hi> only penned, or drawn up, in a method, or form of words, and phraſes, and propoſed to be uſed direction, wiſe, in, or about the Service of God: or elſe, <hi>a Liturgy</hi> impoſed by Authority, under civil mulcts and penalties. The word, <hi>Preſcribed,</hi> is, and may be taken, either in the one, or in the other of theſe ſignifications. Though in the former ſence of the words, the Propoſition ſhould be admitted, yet in the other it will make Anti-Scriptural Divinity. For, <hi>The Service of God performed by an IMPO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SED Liturgy,</hi> is (as hath been formerly proved) ſo far from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>conſonant to holy Scripture,</hi> that the high diſpleaſure of God is here
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:103564:23"/>revealed from Heaven againſt it. But enough of this in the Premiſes. Yet,</p>
            <p n="3">3. (And laſtly) Suppoſe we ſhould be ſo prodigal, as to give away all we have in exception againſt both this and the former Propoſition, (which amounts, as we have found by computing it, to be no ſmall ſumme) and ſo grant Concluſion and all, and all in the Diſputers own ſence (ſo that this be not too unreaſonably exorbitant from his words) yet ſhould we not hereby gratifie him at all in (the beloved of his ſoul) the <hi>Engliſh Service-Book.</hi> For when he ſaith (in this latter Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition) <hi>The Service of God performed by a preſcribed Liturgie, is conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to holy Scripture,</hi> I cannot think that by <hi>A Liturgie,</hi> he mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, <hi>any</hi> Liturgie whatſoever, or that is poſſible to be invented by men (although the expreſſion, whatſoever his meaning be, is not compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent or workman-like) but ſuch <hi>a Liturgie</hi> which ſhall contain nothing in it, either in matter or form, contrary to any precept, or direction found in the Word of God. Becauſe it is too too plain and palpable a caſe, that <hi>the Service of God performed</hi> by any other <hi>Liturgie,</hi> than one of this calculation, cannot be <hi>conſonant to the holy Scripture.</hi> Now then this being his meaning in the <hi>Minor</hi> Propoſition, his Argument with the largeſt indulgence of approbation and conſent, concludes nothing in favour of his Service-Book, nor proveth, that <hi>The Service of God, performed by it, is conſonant to the holy Scripture.</hi> For that there are ſome things contained in this Liturgie, or Book, which are contrary to precepts and directions found in the Word of God, was ſhewed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the beginning of this Diſcourſe; and might be proved in many more particlars, than are there produced. We need go no further than to the <hi>Letany</hi> (ſo called) of which ſuch glorious things are ſpoken by this Author, <hi>pag.</hi> 8. that he ſeems to adore the <hi>fulneſs</hi> of it, as much as <hi>Auſtine</hi> did, <hi>plenitudinem Scripturae,</hi> the fulneſs of the Scriptures themſelves: and more generally, the men of his inſpiration are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent in their <hi>Elogiums</hi> and commendations of this piece, as if in it they ſaw the Service-Book in all her glory. Yet unto him that ſhall weigh it exactly in the ballance of the Sanctuary, it will (I believe) appear to be a very corrupt member, and in which the unclean Spirit of Will-worſhip acteth his part, in ſome things more childiſhly, but in more, more contradictingly to the right rule of Worſhip, than in any other part of the Book. Yea, were there a diligent and narrow ſearch made into it, a juſt volumn might be made of the weak and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy things (only with their ſober and neceſſary explications) that would be found in it. <hi>Firſt,</hi> It is no good <hi>Omen,</hi> that in the very In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription, or Title of it, where it is ordered, or commanded, to be <hi>uſed</hi> on certain dayes, as on <hi>Sundayes, Wedneſdayes,</hi> and <hi>Fridayes,</hi> there is a
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:103564:23"/>manifeſt contrariety to the <hi>Holy Scripture,</hi> which reproveth and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently prohibiteth, <hi>the obſervation of Dayes and Times,</hi> as well as of <hi>Moneths</hi> and <hi>Years, Gal.</hi> 4.10. And why not on <hi>Tueſdayes</hi> and <hi>Thurſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayes,</hi> as well as <hi>on Wedneſdaies</hi> and <hi>Fridaies?</hi> Doubtleſs upon no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter account, than that on which <hi>Jeroboam</hi> offered upon the Altar which he had made in <hi>Bethel, on the fifteenth day of the eighth moneth, even the moneth which he had deviſed of his own heart,</hi> 1 Kings 12.33. If ſuch <hi>devices</hi> as this be not the very quinteſſence, and ſpirit of Will-worſhip, I confeſs I have no underſtanding in the Myſtery. Again, when it is commanded to <hi>be USED on Sundays,</hi> &amp;c. the meaning of the word <hi>uſed</hi> (as the uſe and practice allowed, if not commanded alſo, in thoſe Churches or Chappels, termed <hi>Collegiate,</hi> interpreteth it) is (diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butively) either <hi>ſung</hi> or <hi>ſaid,</hi> the like liberty being granted in theſe words, concerning, <hi>venite exultemus.</hi> Now the Scripture in the New Teſtament maketh a ſlat oppoſition between <hi>praying</hi> and <hi>ſinging, Jam.</hi> 5.13. Nor doth it ſpeak any where of ſinging any thing, but either of <hi>Pſalms,</hi> or <hi>Hymns,</hi> or <hi>Songs.</hi> Now then if the Letany be a Prayer, one or many, and not a Pſalm, Hymn or Song, it cannot be ſung with any <hi>conſonancy to holy Scripture.</hi> Thus we ſee the very door opening into the admired Letany, is polluted: let us vew the Fabrick it ſelf a little, we ſhall ſoon find more irregularities, and pollutions here.</p>
            <p n="1">1. How oft do they that pray by this Letany, tranſgreſs our Saviours rule concerning Prayer, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>uſe no battologies</hi> or need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs repetitions? 1. When the Miniſter prayeth, <hi>O God the Father of Heaven, have mercy upon us miſerable ſinners,</hi> I deſire to know, 1. Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this be an entire Prayer, or a piece of a Prayer. 2. Be it an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire Prayer, or a piece of a Prayer, Whether it is not intended that the People preſent ſhould joyn with him in it, and pray for the ſame thing, when and whileſt he prayeth? If this be ſo, (and I preſume that for ſhame it will not be denied) then it is a battologie, or need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs repetition, for the People immediately, and as it were with the ſame breath, to repeat or pray over the ſame words again; <hi>O God the Father of Heaven,</hi> &amp;c. So then according to this account, if the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter prayeth with the People, as they pray with him, our Saviours rule againſt needleſs repetitions in prayer, is no fewer than four ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral times broken on both hands, within the compaſs of the four firſt pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions, or Prayers of the ſaid Letany. Or if ſuch repetitions as theſe be not vain and needleſs, and ſuch as Chriſt prohibited, I deſire the great Maſter of this piece of devotion, that he will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Diſtinguiſh between repetitions, and repetitions, and define which are <hi>needleſs,</hi> and which are <hi>neceſſary,</hi> and then 2. Give us a ſubſtantial account
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:103564:24"/>that thoſe mentioned, are of the latter, not of the former kind. But to our Query; If the words queried upon, contain an intire Prayer, why do not the People teſtifie their conſent and deſire to have it granted, by ſaying <hi>Amen</hi> at the end of it, (as himſelf ſaith, p. 14. that men are ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to ſay unto ſuch Prayers, and as is more agreeable to <hi>holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> 1 Cor. 14.16.) rather then inſtead thereof to repeat the words of the Prayer? Certainly there cannot be a more pregnant inſtance of a vain and <hi>needleſs repetition</hi> then this, ſince the word <hi>Amen</hi> would ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie altogether as much, yea the very ſame thing which this <hi>repitition</hi> doth. If the ſaid words be to be taken as a Petition onely, and as a member and part of a Prayer, why do the People interrupt the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter in the midſt of his Prayer, ſeeming rather to affront and mock him, by ſaying the ſame words after him, then to expreſs any ſeriouſneſs of Devotion with him? Therefore in this notion of the words, there is in the Peoples repetition of them, a manifeſt inſurrection againſt that Apoſtolical Precept, <hi>Let all things be done decently, and in order.</hi> Or is it <hi>decent</hi> and <hi>orderly,</hi> that the Miniſter ſhould not be ſuffered by the People to finiſh the Prayer which he hath begun, without their inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption? Again,</p>
            <p n="2">2. This unchriſtian miſdemeanour of <hi>battologizing,</hi> is committed ſeven or eight times over, in the repetition of theſe words by the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, <hi>Good Lord deliver us.</hi> For why ſhould not the prolation of them onely once, be as effectual for all needful ends and purpoſes, as the making of ſo many ſounds of the ſame words, ſo nigh together? But it is well, as the caſe ſtands, that the fond ſpirit of VVill-VVorſhip contented himſelf here with ſo few miſcarriages in <hi>vain repetitions,</hi> as ſeven or eight, when as, upon as good an account in reaſon, he might have multiplied them to ſeventeen or eighteen, or to a greater num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber: at which ſtone, being blind, he ſtumbled ſoon after, in preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing theſe words, <hi>We beſeech thee to hear us good Lord,</hi> to be repeated twenty, or one and twenty times over, within the compaſs of ſo much devotion as may be diſpatched without making haſte, within the ſpace of half a quarter of an hour. But</p>
            <p n="3">3. Beſides theſe groſs and palpable <hi>Battologies,</hi> which cannot light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly eſcape any mans eye, that doth but curſorily view that highly honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, but more juſtly condemned, Model of Devotion, the <hi>Letany:</hi> there are ſeveral others obnoxious enough to a little obſervation. For, 1. Preſently after requeſt here made for deliverance <hi>from all evil and miſchief, and from ſin;</hi> another requeſt is made for deliverance from ſome <hi>evils,</hi> and ſome <hi>ſins,</hi> as from <hi>Pride, Vain-glory, Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>from Fornication, and all other deadly ſin,</hi> [as if Pride, Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:103564:24"/>Malice, Envy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> were but ſins <hi>venial.</hi>] By the way, They that are ſo deſirous to cover the ſhame of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Parentage of their ſarling Letany, much forget themſelves, to ſuffer ſo expreſs a linea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ent of her Mothers feature to be ſeen in her face, as the making onely of ſome ſins <hi>deadly,</hi> (which ſuppoſeth others to be <hi>venial.</hi>) 2. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter deliverance begg'd <hi>from the crafts and aſſaults of the Devil,</hi> the like deliverance is within two or three lines begg'd again <hi>from all the deceits of the Devil;</hi> and afterwards, <hi>from thoſe evils which the craft and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilty of the Devil worketh againſt us.</hi> 3. After prayer made for delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance <hi>from contempt of Gods Word and Commandment,</hi> prayer is here a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain made that we may <hi>diligently live after his Commandments;</hi> and the third time, that we may <hi>amend our lives according to his holy Word.</hi> Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages and expreſſions ſymbolizing in words, ſence, and meaning, as near as theſe, found in the <hi>conceived Prayer</hi> of an Anti-formiſt, would be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>tautologies,</hi> to the great diſgrace and contempt of it, by perſons who have addicted themſelves to <hi>Liturgical</hi> (I had almoſt ſaid, <hi>Lethargical</hi>) Devotions. 4. VVhen prayer hath been here made unto God <hi>to give and preſerve to our uſe THE FRUITS OF THE EARTH, ſo as in due time we may enjoy them;</hi> we are compelled to pray again in dry weather, <hi>for ſuch moderate rain and ſhowers, that we may RECEIVE THE FRUITS OF THE EARTH to our comfort,</hi> &amp;c. and yet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain in wet weather, <hi>for ſuch weather whereby we may RECEIVE THE FRUITS OF THE EARTH in due ſeaſon;</hi> and yet after all this, <hi>That our Land may yeild us HER FRUITS of increaſe.</hi> 5. After the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple have pray'd, <hi>Have mercy upon us,</hi> (being beholding to their Miniſter for a Vocative-caſe) they muſt pray out of hand yet again, <hi>Lord have mercy upon us;</hi> and for all this, yet again, <hi>Chriſt have mercy upon us;</hi> and after all theſe agains, yet again (once more) <hi>Lord have mercy upon us:</hi> and now all the Beads of this ſtring are told. 6. This Prayer, <hi>O Lord ariſe, help us and deliver us for thy Names ſake;</hi> is preſently after corrected and amended onely thus, <hi>O Lord ariſe, help us and deliver us for thine Honour.</hi> 7. When we have prayed, <hi>From our Enemies defend us, O Chriſt;</hi> we muſt pray unto Almighty God, (as if our Letany did a little <hi>Socinianize</hi>) <hi>Save and deliver us from—the hands of our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</hi> 8. About the middle of this Letany, after the thick and ſhort Prayers, the Miniſter, as if the People and he had been idle untill now, or at leaſt about ſome other buſineſs then praying, admoniſheth his People to pray; ſaying unto them, <hi>Let us pray.</hi> 9. (And laſtly, to paſs by ſeveral other impertinent <hi>Duplicats</hi> and <hi>Multiplicats,</hi> or vain repetitions of Petitions within the compaſs of the <hi>Letany</hi> onely) When the Miniſter and People ſhall have prayed with the uttermoſt devotion
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:103564:25"/>they can make between them, for <hi>Charles our moſt gracious King and Governour, for our gracious Queen Katharine, Mary the Queen-Mother, James Duke of Yorke,</hi> &amp;c. they muſt recruit their Devotions very ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily, or elſe they will pray the ſecond time (which is not far off) but coldly for <hi>our moſt gracious Soveraign Lord King Charles, our gracious Queen Katharine,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Neither is this admired piece of Devotion ſo notoriouſly defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med (as we have ſeen) with Tautologies and empty Repetitions onely, it hath ſundry other Ailments and Diſeaſes hanging upon it. 1. All thoſe eight Petitions or Prayers (if ſuch they be) put into the mouth of the Miniſter, unto which ſo many <hi>Good-Lord-deliver-us's</hi> are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned, as far as the Miniſter uttereth or prayeth them, are abſolute and groſs Non-ſence, having no Verb at all in them, onely the People are enjoyned to ſupply the defects of their Miniſter, and to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prop his pendulous words with a principal Verb; and ſo between the Premiſes of the one, and the Concluſion of the other, we have (with much ado) a Syllogiſm of Prayer formed. That the Miniſter ſhould pray by halves, or make half a Prayer, and the People pray ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther half Prayer, and theſe two halfs be clapt together to make a whole Prayer, is (certainly) a new-fangled device of praying, and ſuch whereof the Scripture, yea, and all Principles of Reaſon, not ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitionized, are aſhamed. But, 2. Though <hi>Good-Lord-deliver-us,</hi> joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the preceding words of the Miniſter, make a competent and grammatical ſence together; yet thoſe one and twenty Some-whats, (for Prayers they are not, and what diſtinct appellation to give them, I know not) which are relieved with the like number of <hi>We-beſeech-thee to-hear-us-Good-Lords,</hi> do not of themſelves make any ſenſe at all, nor any very good ſence in conjunction with the words aſſigned unto them for their relief: For to ſay, <hi>That it may pleaſe thee</hi> to do this and that, <hi>We beſeech thee to hear us good Lord,</hi> is little better then a Soloeciſm; at the beſt but an unuſual and harſh conſtruction.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Here are ſeveral expreſſions and paſſages beſides, not ſo conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate or well-digeſted. 1. To pray to be delivered from <hi>Deadly Sins,</hi> (which ſuppoſeth the diſtinction of Sins into <hi>venial</hi> and <hi>mortal,</hi> to be conſonant to the Scriptures) ſounds rather Pontifician then Proteſtant Devotion (though I think the diſtinction may in a ſence be admitted) this was touched before. 2. To pray unto God <hi>to preſerve all that travel by Land or by Water;</hi> is it not to pray for High-way-men and Thieves, Pirates, and Murtherers (if they be travelling either by <hi>Land or Water</hi>) that they may eſcape the danger of being ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended and puniſhed for their wickedneſs, and conſequently that
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:103564:25"/>they may have peace and continue undiſturbed in their horrid practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as well as honeſt and harmleſs men in ſuch a condition? 3. Theſe expreſſions, <hi>By thy Agony and bloody Sweat, by thy Croſs and Paſſion,</hi> &amp;c. be they intended, whether <hi>ſenſu Mediatorio, Adjurativo, re-memorativo,</hi> or in what ſence ſoever, make no good ſound in the ears of a good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, eſpecially that is tender and unlearned. 4. Every perſon that is enjoyned to pray for the <hi>ſending down of the HEALTHFUL Spirit of Grace upon our Biſhops and Curats,</hi> &amp;c. hardly underſtands, in what ſence, why or how, the <hi>Spirit</hi> of God is here termed <hi>healthful.</hi> 5. That God ſhould be conſidered in his power of <hi>working Great Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles,</hi> when he is deſired to <hi>ſend down his Spirit upon our Biſhops and Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rats,</hi> &amp;c. Doth it imply (for it ſeems ſo to do) that God <hi>worketh a great Miracle when he ſendeth down his healthful Spirit upon any of our Biſhops and Curats?</hi> &amp;c. 6. (And laſtly) That <hi>Biſhops</hi> ſhould be here twice prayed for, whenas <hi>the Lords of the Council, and all the Nobility,</hi> have only one prayer allowed them, and this a very ſhort and ſimple one, may reaſonably be imputed to their great need of being often prayed for, their <hi>wants</hi> being great and many, and their temptations many through their great <hi>abundance:</hi> which might likewiſe unhappily occaſion their deſire, that the Prayer for them, and their <hi>Curats</hi> (for ſo they are wont to interpret, <hi>Paſtors and Miniſters of the Church</hi>) might have the precedency of the Prayer of the <hi>Lords of the Council and all the Nobility.</hi> Thus much (by the way) concerning the <hi>Letany,</hi> the Head Quarters of the <hi>Service-Book,</hi> where the higheſt ſtraines of Devotion, that rule here, are ſuppoſed to lodge and reſide. That they ſo much ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire it who are ſo deep in love with it, needs be no mans admiration. It is a riming Proverb (I ſuppoſe) of the ſame race and deſcent with the Book it ſelf:
<q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Si quis amat ranam, ranam putat eſſe Dianam.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>One ſilly Frog who dotes in love, will ſwear,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Diana's</hi> beauty ſhineth not more clear.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q> I have at (preſent) taken notice only of a few of the deformed li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neaments in the face of it; in my ſurvey of it, I diſcovered many more: but thoſe mentioned I judge competent to break the ſnare, which the zealous and importune commendations of it by ſome, who have (moſt unworthily) enſlaved themſelves in Devotion to it, may prove unto others, who (haply) would be more enclinable to worſhip God purely, and with acceptation, were not this uncouth Form of
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:103564:26"/>Devotion with ſwelling words of vanity obtruded on them. Never was there (I verily believe) a Liturgie, or piece of any Liturgie, of ſo wild and barbarous, of ſo miſhapen, odd and diſordered a contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance, that ever preſumed to look the world in the face; or at leaſt, that was gloried over at the tenth part of that rate, at which ſo many men of commendable parts, learning, and underſtanding otherwiſe, make boaſt of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Letany. The Apoſtles expoſtulatory queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the <hi>Galatians,</hi> might be very ſeaſonably put to them at this turn, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.1.</p>
            <p>We now return to the purſuit of our main undertaking, where we brake off from it upon occaſion of that diverſion, with which the Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er hath been made acquainted. We had proceeded ſo far in aſſerting it, as the incommunicable Prerogative of God, to appoint and enjoyn his own Worſhip, that there remained nothing of what was further intended herein, but only the ſatisfying of ſuch Arguments, or preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, by which this Prerogative of God is attempted to be overthrown, by entitling men to a right of power to impoſe Worſhip of their own preſcribing, as well as He.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> The examples of the godly Kings in <hi>Juda,</hi> as of <hi>David, Aſa, Jehoſhaphat, Hezekiah, Joſiah,</hi> &amp;c. interpoſing and impoſing, in Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous affairs, are frequently imployed for the juſtification of the impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of Forms of Worſhip by the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Magiſtrate, and this under very grievous mulcts and penalties, at this day. I anſwer, they may be imployed for ſuch a purpoſe, and yet to very little or no purpoſe at all. For,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Theſe Kings had holy Prophets amongſt them, immediately in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired by God, who from time to time, upon all occaſions, were ſent unto them with the mind of God in their mouths, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 22.5. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.4, 5. &amp; 12.1. 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 19.2, 6, 7, &amp;c. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 15.1, 2. &amp; 18.7, 18, &amp;c. <hi>and</hi> 19.2. <hi>and</hi> 20.14, 15, &amp;c. <hi>and</hi> 25.7, 8, 9, 15. <hi>and</hi> 26.5. <hi>and</hi> 34.21, 22, 23, &amp;c. Whereas Magiſtrates in theſe dayes have no ſuch <hi>internuncij</hi> between God, and them, infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly to declare his mind unto them in difficult caſes.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They had the mouth of God himſelf alwayes near unto them by <hi>Urim</hi> and <hi>Thummim;</hi> by conſulting by theſe, they might know his mind in all caſes of concernment, and be reſolved in all their doubts, without any danger of miſtake. See and compare, <hi>Num.</hi> 27.21. <hi>and</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23.2, 4, 9. <hi>and</hi> 30.7. <hi>and</hi> 28.6. <hi>Surplice</hi> and <hi>Lawn-ſleeves</hi> are not <hi>Urim</hi> and <hi>Thummim.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. However the ſaid Kings interpoſed with their Authority in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:103564:26"/>of Religion, yet they never impoſed upon their People any new Form of Worſhip, either of their own or other mens deviſing: but on the contrary ſtill interdicted and prohibited all ſuch kinds, methods, and manners of Worſhip which were of Humane Invention, as being provoking in the ſight of God, defacing, aboliſhing, and deſtroying all their accoutrements, and whatſoever was relating unto ſuch Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, either in a way of allurement or provocation, or of ſubſerviency in any kind; yea, they ſpared not the Prieſts themſelves, the Grand Promoters of this Worſhip, but did ſevere execution upon them alſo, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 13.2. compared with 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 23.20. and 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 34.5. Now then to reaſon thus; The Kings of <hi>Juda</hi> had power to enjoyn the Worſhip of God appointed and commanded by God himſelf, and to aboliſh all other kinds of Worſhip of a Forreign and Humane extracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Therefore <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Magiſtrates have a right of Power to appoint and in joyn what Forms or Kinds of Worſhip they pleaſe, whether they be preſcribed and appointed by God or no; to reaſon thus (I ſay) plainly argueth, that men have taken ſome bribe, or other, to blind the eyes of their minds and underſtandings.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Whatſoever was done by the godly Kings of <hi>Juda</hi> in matters of Religion, was plainly commanded by God himſelf in the Law of <hi>Moſes:</hi> in what they did upon this account, they neither added to, nor took from his Word. See <hi>Exod.</hi> 23.24. <hi>Deut.</hi> 7.5. <hi>and</hi> 12.2, 3. <hi>Exod.</hi> 34.13. And for the Commands of God, relating unto his external Worſhip, and to the preſervation hereof in purity, which were deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto the <hi>Jews,</hi> other than ſuch which the Law and Light of Nature alſo teacheth (which were not many, if any in this kind) are not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly not oblieging upon any other Nation, but are no ſufficient Warrant unto any to practiſe, or put in execution, the things commanded in them. One reaſon whereof, may be, becauſe they were given unto the <hi>Jews</hi> with ſpecial reference unto the counſel and deſign of God in, and about that Nation and People, and are not ſerviceable for any deſign, which at this day he hath on foot, in, or about any Nation in the World; as (for inſtance) to make any of them <hi>typically holy.</hi> I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe that no conſidering man will affirm, that thoſe Laws, or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, laid down, <hi>Deut.</hi> 13.5. <hi>and v.</hi> 8, 9, 10. <hi>and v.</hi> 15, 16, 17. which were as effectually binding unto the <hi>Jews,</hi> and their Rulers, as any Moral Precept, will juſtifie in theſe dayes any Nation or Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, that ſhall do the things contained in them. So then, that the godly Kings of <hi>Juda</hi> did that in matters of Religion, lawfully, yea or commendably, which they were by God commanded to do, is only a prevaricating Argument, to prove, that <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Magiſtrates may do
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:103564:27"/>that, either commendably, or lawfully in matters of the ſame concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which God hath not commanded them.</p>
            <p n="5">5. When theſe Kings did command the obſervation of thoſe very things by the People, which God himſelf had commanded them in his Law, the People, (at leaſt ſuch as feared God, and beſt underſtood themſelves among them) did not ſo much mind the Kings Authority in commanding them, as the Command of God himſelf concerning them. When that good King <hi>Joſiah</hi> made a <hi>Covenant before the Lord, to walk after the Lord and keep his Commandments,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and cauſed all that were preſent of</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>and</hi> Benjamin, <hi>to ſtand to it,</hi> it is expreſly ſaid, That <hi>the inhabitonts of</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>did according to the Covenant of God, the God of their Fathers;</hi> implying, that it was the Covenant or Commandment of God for the doing of thoſe things, which the King cauſed them to promiſe they would do, which principally moved them to that obedience which they yeelded unto them, and not the moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or (if we will not be content without more than is due) the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of the King. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 34.31, 32.</p>
            <p n="6">6. The Kings we ſpake of, were Types of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> who was as well a Prophet, as a King: and in this reſpect it was proper for them to take care of, and to interpoſe in, matters relating to the Worſhip of God, aſwell as to the Civil Government. But ſince <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s coming in the fleſh, types either in perſons, or in things, have no place in the Church. So that to veſt a power of regulating and ordering the Worſhip of God in <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Kings, is to make them Types of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and conſequently to deny, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> is come in the fleſh. Upon the like account the High Prieſts among the <hi>Jews,</hi> being alſo Types of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> who was as well a King as a Prieſt, the better to anſwer and fill their relation to their Great Anti-type, were admitted by God into part and fellowſhip of the Civil Government. But for Miniſters of the Goſpel to admit of politick inveſtitures, or to accept or exerciſe any Civil Power, is to <hi>Judaïze,</hi> and to <hi>deny him that bought them,</hi> to be as yet come into the World. But that the Kings of <hi>Judah</hi> were Types of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> is evident, and withal generally acknowledged in the perſons of the two firſt of that race, which was in ſpecial manner appointed by God to ſit upon that Throne, <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Solomon:</hi> and there is little reaſon to queſtion the ſame relation in the reſt, conſidering that they alſo were Heads over the ſame typical Nation, and exerciſed the ſame Bipartite power in governing it, which the other did; not to add that they were alſo in their Loy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, when they acted in the typical relation mentioned, and ſo in a ſence (frequently owned in the Scripture) were that, and did that, which they (their fore-fathers) were, and did.</p>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:103564:27"/>
            <p n="7">7. The Nation and People over which theſe Kings reigned, were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned, and accordingly prepared and fitted by God, to be made a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and People <hi>typically holy;</hi> that is, preſignificant, or pre-figurative, by and in their external and ceremonial Holineſs and Conformity to the Worſhip of God then preſcribed unto them, of the real ſanctity and holineſs, as well inward as outward, which was to be found in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Churches, and in the People of God under the Goſpel. This <hi>typical</hi> conſideration of the Nation of the <hi>Jews,</hi> is more then overtur'd or ſparingly intimated in the Scriptures: The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> plainly aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerteth it, where he ſaith, <hi>For we</hi> [Chriſtians and true Believers] <hi>are the Circumciſion</hi> [that is, the People prefigured by thoſe that were <hi>cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed,</hi> meaning the <hi>Jews;</hi> the Anti-type being often expreſſed by the name of the Type, as <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.28, 29. <hi>Jer.</hi> 30.9. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 34.23, 24. <hi>&amp;</hi> 37.24, 25. <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.14. <hi>&amp;</hi> 17.2. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.10. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.9. <hi>&amp;</hi> 3.9. with others] <hi>which worſhip God in the Spirit, and rejoyce in Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Philip.</hi> 3.3. See further to this purpoſe, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.9. and what Expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors generally, and more eſpecially the <hi>Dutch</hi> Annotators write hereon. Now to order this Nation ſo, that it might ſerve the Counſel of God in its typical Relation ſpecified, upon the better and more ſignificant terms, it was neceſſary that by a ſtrong hand, and by the Authority and Power of their chief Rulers, they ſhould be kept in a Conformity to the Law of God concerning his Worſhip (eſpecially) and not ſuffered (as far as might be) to corrupt themſelves with any falſe Worſhip, or by going a whoring after any ſtrange God. And it was the rather ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary that they ſhould be thus reſtrained from polluting themſelves with Idolatry in any kind, becauſe they were (more generally) exceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſively prone to break out in this way of ſinning, and had many temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations from the Nations round about them, to entice and provoke them accordingly; the means of Grace (in the mean time) by which men are, contrary to their ſinful propenſions, drawn to love, &amp; fear, and cleave faſt, and cloſe unto God, being but very ſparingly, and by ſcant meaſures, in reſpect of Goſpel-allowance, vouchſafed unto them. Now then, there being nothing of all this long ſtory, belonging unto, or found in Chriſtian Churches, who live under Chriſtian Kings, but all things contrary or otherwiſe, it is very importune, and againſt the grain of all reaſon, to ſubject theſe Churches unto theſe Kings upon the ſame terms on which the Church or Nation of the <hi>Jews</hi> was by God himſelf ſubjected under theirs. The Rule in reaſon is, <hi>Contrariorum contraria [non eadem] ſunt conſequentia:</hi> Contraries have Conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, not the ſame, but as contrary as themſelves.</p>
            <p n="8">8. The Kings of <hi>Judah</hi> were nominated and appointed by God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:103564:28"/>immediately unto this Kingdom: the Throne whereof was ſetled by him upon <hi>David</hi> and his Poſterity, as an heritage for ever, (1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.12. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.12, 16. 1 <hi>King.</hi> 2.4. <hi>&amp;</hi> 8.25. and elſewhere:) So that though the People accepted them [reſpectively and ſucceſſively] for their Kings, and inveſted them with their Enſigns of Royalty, and ſo are ſaid to have <hi>made</hi> them <hi>Kings;</hi> yet their Right and Title to the Kingdom, was given unto them by God without the People, and before they had declared their acceptance or owning of them. Now then, as they were Kings extraordinarily called by God, without any depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance upon, or mediation of the People by their election unto the Throne: ſo their Authority and Power were in an extraordinary way alſo, and by an unuſual line, meaſured and ſet out unto them. For as God, when he unbareth his Arm, and worketh Miracles, is obſerved in ſuch works as theſe, to exceed that rate of Perfection at which he work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in the ordinary and ſtanding courſe of his Providence, and in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction with inferiour and ſecond Cauſes, (many fair overtures, if not full proofs whereof, the Scripture affordeth us, and the reaſon like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe of the thing, is not far of, although we ſhall not now touch it:) So likewiſe when he giveth Authority and Power unto Kings and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces immediately by himſelf, it is very reaſonable to conceive that he giveth it by a larger meaſure, then when he imparts and communicats it by the People: For, as obſerving the courſe of Nature, he cannot cauſe a Sheep to bring forth a Lion, although by his unlimitted Power he is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to create a Lion of what ſtature, and ſtrength, and fierceneſs he pleaſeth: So when he joyneth himſelf with the People in deriving Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority and Power unto Kings (which he always doth, when he uſeth their mediation in the election of Kings) he can derive no more of theſe unto them, then what is competent for the People to derive with him; yea, no more then what he maketh the People willing as well as able to derive with him: However, (as hath been ſaid) if he pleaſeth to make Kings immediately, of and by himſelf, without the People, he may inveſt them with what proportion of both he pleaſeth. So then, the meaſure or proportion of Authority and Power which was veſted by God in, and accordingly exerciſed by the Kings of <hi>Judah,</hi> is no ſteady ground whereon to warrant the ſame proportion or meaſure unto Chriſtian Kings. The reaſon hereof hath been expreſſed already; namely, becauſe no King of this denomination received his call unto his Royal Dignity immediately from God, as thoſe Kings received theirs; but all of them <hi>mediante Populo,</hi> mediately by and from the People: and conſequently can have no other, no more, or greater Power then what is or was inherently in the People, and lawful for
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:103564:28"/>them to part with unto them. And certain it is, that no perſon can lawfully or reaſonably give a power unto any man to regulate his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience about the Worſhip of God, as he pleaſeth; himſelf having no power in this kind, but onely to regulate it according to the Will and Commandment of God. Neither had the Kings of <hi>Judah</hi> themſelves any ſuch power as this given unto them by God, as hath been formerly ſhewed.</p>
            <p n="9">9. (And laſtly) Notwithſtanding all the great power they had from God, yet when any of theſe Kings did cauſe their People to enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Religious Covenant or Oath, they did it not againſt the wills, no nor without the conſent of their People; yea, theſe were as forward and active in the buſineſs as the Kings themſelves: <hi>And they</hi> [King <hi>Aſa,</hi> with the generality or Body of his People, as appears from the Context, both ſubſequent and preceding] <hi>entered into a Covenant to ſeek the Lord God of their Fathers, with all their heart, and with all their ſoul; That whoſoever would not ſeek the Lord God of Iſrael, ſhould be put to death, whether ſmall or great, whether man or woman. And they ſware unto the Lord with a loud voice, and with ſhouting, and with Trumpets, and with Cornets. And ALL Judah rejoyced at the Oath: for they had ſworn with all their heart,</hi> &amp;c. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 15.12, 13, 14, 15. So that the King impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed nothing upon the People, but what they moſt freely, yea moſt joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully impoſed upon themſelves. And that is obſervable by the way, that there is no other penalty or puniſhment any where threatned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt any tranſgreſſor of any Order, Edict, or Impoſition, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Religion, or the Worſhip and Service of God, publiſhed by any of the ſaid good Kings, either with or without their People, but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that of <hi>death;</hi> which is the puniſhment expreſly commanded by God himſelf to be inflicted in ſuch caſes; I mean upon Idolaters law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully convicted, (<hi>Deut.</hi> 17.2, 3, 4, 5, 6.) Yea, <hi>Jehoſaphat</hi> would not ſo much as <hi>appoint Singers unto the Lord</hi> to go <hi>before the Army,</hi> without <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultation</hi> firſt had with the People about it, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 20.21. See alſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> 2 Chro. 30.2, 4, 5. They who would compell the good Kings of <hi>Judah</hi> to inveſt <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Magiſtrates with their power, in matters of Religion, do very unworthily in reſtraining them from in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructing theſe Magiſtrates by their worthy Examples in and about the exerciſe of this power. But I truſt that from henceforth theſe good Kings will be innocent from the great offence of ſtrengthning the hand of <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Magiſtrates in oppreſſing the Conſciences of their good Subjects with penal Impoſitions in matters of Religion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Some plead, That God hath admitted <hi>Caeſar</hi> (the <hi>Chriſtian
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:103564:29"/>Caeſar</hi>) into part and fellowſhip with himſelf in matters of his Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, ſo far, as with the advice of his Spiritual Senators, (his Lord-Biſhops) to make what by-Laws in matters of this nature, he pleaſeth, and to impoſe any Form, one or more, of Divine Worſhip, upon his Subjects, under what Penalties he thinks fit; ſo that the Worſhip impoſed in theſe Forms be <hi>conſonant</hi> to the Word of God. Theſe men would fain incorporate this notion into the Body of our Faith, That the things of <hi>Caeſar</hi> would otherwiſe be too narrow and inconſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, for a Perſon of ſo auguſt and ſacred an inveſtiture, unleſs it be ſuppoſed that the Almighty giveth unto him the right hand of Fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip in ordering the Affairs of his Worſhip, in forming and reforming, in changing and altering it at his pleaſure; yea, and in puniſhing with great ſeverity, thoſe that ſhall not bow down to his preſent eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, whatever it be.</p>
            <p>Although the ſpirit of this plea hath been quenched already, yet let us take the pains to draw a little more water to caſt upon it. There ſore,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Maſters of this Plea, in pleading the Cauſe of their Tythes, often make uſe of an <hi>Emblem,</hi> which though colourable onely for that ſervice, will be of a real accommodation here: The Eagle ſetting her Neſt on fire, and ſo deſtroying her young ones, with a burning Coal, which ſtuck (though ſhe minded it not) to the piece of Fleſh that ſhe had ſacrilegiouſly ſnatch'd from off the Altar, and carried to her Neſt, upon which the diſaſter happened; is an apt Reſemblance of thoſe Calamities &amp; Judgements which ſooner or later fall upon the Houſes and Families of ſuch Kings and Princes and Grandees of the World, who intrench upon the Quarters of Him whoſe Name is <hi>Jealous,</hi> and cannot be content without being adored as <hi>Domini utriuſque Seculi,</hi> as having Dominion over the things of both Worlds. If men will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to ſet their poſts too near unto the poſts of God, he will up with them again, and burn them with fire. Inſtances hereof may be found in the premiſes. But,</p>
            <p n="2">2. It never yet was, nor (moſt certainly) ever will be proved, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from the Scriptures, or from any Principle of ſound Reaſon, that Kings or Magiſtrates are by God joyned in Commiſſion with himſelf, to impoſe Models or Forms of Worſhip, ſuch as they pleaſe [onely with this Condition, That they think or ſuppoſe them to be agreeable to the Scriptures] upon their fellow-Creatures, (the Sons and Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Men) yea, upon ſuch Perſons who in all likelihood, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to all experience in like caſes, know and underſtand the mind and will of God concerning his Worſhip, much more perfectly then
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:103564:29"/>themſelves; yea, and whom God hath commiſſioned to teach and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct them in his Worſhip and Service [I mean the faithful, able, and learned Miniſters of the Goſpel.] But this Nail hath already been hammered ſufficiently.</p>
            <p n="3">3. As for thoſe Spiritual Senators, mentioned in the Argument by the name of <hi>Lord Biſhops,</hi> without whoſe advice the Commiſſion gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to Kings and Magiſtrates (as is pretended) to umpire the Worſhip of God, is (it ſeems) ſuperſeded; the Scripture is ſo far from authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing or appointing them to be Aſſiſtants or Adviſers unto Kings and Magiſtrates, in or about the execution of ſuch a Commiſſion, that it taketh no knowledge of any ſuch Generation of Men, unleſs it be to ſhut the door againſt them, that they might not get into the world, (<hi>Mat.</hi> 20.25, 26.) though ſince they have committed Burglary, and broke open this door, and are gotten in the Houſe of God, to the great anoyance and diſturbance of the peace of it. The Scripture maketh mention onely of one in thoſe days, who did <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (3 <hi>John</hi> 9.) wiſh, or deſire, to be a Lord-Biſhop; whoſe character was, that he would not ſuffer faithful Miniſters of the Goſpel in the Church, no not the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> himſelf, who was ſo peculiarly loved by Chriſt, but <hi>prated againſt him with malicious words.</hi> And to me it is the firſt-born amongſt many <hi>Arguments,</hi> that ſuch a kind of Officers in the Church, as theſe men pretend themſelves to be, were never intended by the Lord <hi>Chriſt;</hi> namely, that neither by Chriſt himſelf, nor by any of his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, he hath given any name whereby the Church ſhould know or call them, or diſtinguiſh them from others. It oppoſeth all the believing faculties of my Soul, to think that Chriſt ſhould either forget or neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect to mention the prime and Head-Officers of his Church, (as our Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops (ſo called) conclude themſelves to be; and as indeed they are, if they be any at all) by an appropriate and diſtinct name, whenas he hath provided and given ſuch names unto thoſe that are eſteemed ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate and inferiour to them, as <hi>Paſtors, Teachers,</hi> and <hi>Deacons.</hi> For thoſe Apocryphal Officers we ſpeak of, have ſacrilegiouſly robb'd thoſe true Officers of the Church, <hi>Paſtors</hi> and <hi>Teachers,</hi> of the name <hi>Biſhop,</hi> which was given in common unto them; and having alter'd the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty of the Divine Conſecration of it, have ſanctified and devoted it unto themſelves, leſt being <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, without a name, they ſhould be found <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> alſo, ſpurious and illegiti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ate. Beſides, as Chriſt left ſuch Officers no name, ſo neither hath he left them any work. For he ſufficiently provided for all the ſpiritual occaſions of his Church in all Ages, by thoſe Officers whom the Apoſtle expreſly nameth, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.11. Read this verſe, with the three next following, and you will find
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:103564:30"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:103564:30"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:103564:31"/>the Biſhop to be a ſuperfluous, and very impertinent Officer, in, and for the Church. But as being left by <hi>Chriſt</hi> without a name, they made a diſhoneſt ſhift (as we have heard) to get one: ſo being left without work alſo, they found out an imployment likewiſe for themſelves; as namely, to ſerve the Church with indifferent [that is, with imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, and needleſs] things, with a few <hi>harmleſs</hi> Ceremonies <hi>[lenitate verbi triſtitiam rei mitigante]</hi> as Tippits, and Rochets, Caps and Hoods, Black Gowns and White Surplices, Croſſings and Cringings, Stand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings up, and Kneelings down, with ſeveral others of the like profound calculation: all which both joyntly, and ſeverally, are as effectual and proper to build up the Church in Unity, Love, and Peace, as the confuſion of Tongues was to promote the building of the Tower of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel,</hi> and the poyſon of Aſps to nouriſh and preſerve the natural Life of Man. As for their imployment about Ordination, which together with their Name and Title of <hi>Biſhop,</hi> they have injuriouſly wreſted out of the hand of thoſe true Officers of <hi>Chriſt, Paſtors</hi> and <hi>Teachers</hi> (with their reſpective Congregations) this takes up ſo little of their time, and ſo ſeldom engageth them, that had they not found themſelves other work, which might laſt all the year long, and ſo fill up the void ſpaces between Ordination and Ordination (which the management of Ceremonies, as they trouble themſelves, and others about them, doth) the inconſiderableneſs of their work would have rendred their importune and loud claim of grandure and great things in the Church, very obnoxious. Therefore (certainly) that kind of Officer we ſpeak of, having neither Name, nor Work in the Church, aſſigned unto him by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> was not deſigned by him to any part or fellowſhip with thoſe that bear Office here.</p>
            <p n="4">4. There was a generation of men in the world, who were wont to <hi>make the King glad with their wickedneſs, and the Princes with their lies, Hoſ.</hi> 7.3. I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> our Lord <hi>Biſhops</hi> be not the ſervants of this impiety, the world is uncharitable, and the thing it ſelf next to a miracle. For they lie under greater temptations, to enſnare them in this kind, than fleſh and blood (ordinarily) is willing to reſiſt. And the deſires of the great things of the world, unto which they are advanced, (for theſe things are not wont to be found of thoſe that ſeek them not) proclaim them to be no mighty men of valour to reſiſt temptations. Therefore in this reſpect alſo they are not competent to make <hi>Adviſers</hi> unto Kings or Rulers in any their conſultations about forming or ſetting forth the Worſhip of God. <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſimum genus Conſiliariorum Adulatores.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. The Worſhip of God being of a moſt tender reſentment with thoſe, who truly know and fear him, and tremble to offend him, theſe
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:103564:31"/>men being violent and importune obtruders of Forms and Ceremonies, are the moſt unfit men in the world to be called unto Counſel, when this affair is to come under conſideration.</p>
            <p n="6">6 Concerning the pretended narrowneſs of the Authority and Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Kings, in caſe they ſhould be confined within a Politique ſphere, and not ſtretch themſelves unto Spiritual things alſo: I anſwer; 1. That God underſtandeth better than the wiſeſt of men, what mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, or degree of Power maketh, both the moſt commodious, and the moſt comely proportion for any man: and (doubtleſs) unto whomſoever he giveth it, in this proportion he giveth it. Therefore for any man to call that <hi>narrow,</hi> or <hi>unmeet,</hi> which God in his Word judgeth large enough, and comely, is an unſavoury preſumption. Are our weights and meaſures better, or more exact, than his? 2. I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that Kings and Princes would find full imployment for their Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority and Power, within their Politick ſphears (reſpectively) work enough to fill their heads, hearts and hands, were they conſcientiouſly intent upon what God, yea and their own honour, comfort and peace, require of them here. But, 3. (and laſtly for this) If God ſhould allow unto <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Kings and Magiſtrates, a right of power to impoſe Forms of Worſhip upon men, he ſhould allow them a greater power or liberty than he hath, or hath judged meet to leave unto, himſelf. For if Kings may impoſe Forms of Worſhip, they may impoſe, one while one, and when they pleaſe, another. For who, or what, ſhall hinder them? For if God hath given unto them a grant for ſuch un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, doubtleſs he hath not limited, or confined them in this grant unto one Form only: not hath he preſcribed any one Form determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately, which it ſhall be lawful for them to impoſe, and not any other. Such a conceit as this, never (I ſuppoſe) entred into any of thoſe heads which belong unto the hearts, out of which the ſad Doctrine of Impoſitions do proceed. Therefore if Kings and Magiſtrates may im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, their Impoſitions, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Forms of Worſhip impoſed, may be as nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous, as the Idolatrous Altars of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were of old, which are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to <hi>heaps</hi> [of ſtones, gathered up and laid in rowes] <hi>in the ſurrows of the field. Hoſ.</hi> 12.11. Yea, if they ſhall vary and change their Forms never ſo often, as (ſuppoſe) every day in the year, eſpecially if they ſee cauſe (as very probably they may if they look narrowly) or ſhall imagine or think they ſee cauſe, ſo to do, who can juſtly reprove them for it? They may (in Scripture phraſe) <hi>ſhake, not the Earth only, but alſo Heaven,</hi> as oft as they pleaſe: they may diſtu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>b and amu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e the World with Mutations and Changes in the Worſhip of God with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out end. Whereas God himſelf hath given ſecurity unto the World,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:103564:32"/>That he will not alter the terms of his Worſhip declared in the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, or ever impoſe any new Model or Form hereof upon the children of men, whilſt the World ſtandeth. And whereas he interpreteth this ſaying of his, <hi>Yet once more I ſhake not the Earth only, but alſo Heaven,</hi> in the notion of a <hi>Promiſe; But now he hath PROMISED, ſaying,</hi> &amp;c. (<hi>Heb.</hi> 12.26.) there is little queſtion but that part of the Grace, or good thing here <hi>promiſed,</hi> conſiſteth in this, that he will <hi>once more</hi> [only, or, but <hi>once more] ſhake the Heavens</hi> (theſe reſtrictive praticles, but <hi>only, &amp;c.</hi> being frequently omitted, and left to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood) By <hi>ſhaking the Heavens,</hi> he meaneth the diſſolving or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moving, the preſent external frame or form of Religion, or of his Worſhip, together with the great commotions, or high workings in the mindes and conſciences of men, that would enſue hereupon. But e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough in anſwer to the ſecond Argument.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Some plead aloud, and with no ſmall confidence, for the joynt-intereſt of the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Magiſtrate with God himſelf, in impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Forms of Worſhip, by an Argument to this effect: That which is lawful, may be lawfully commanded or impoſed by the Civil Magiſtrate: But the Worſhip of God performed by ſtinted Forms, if theſe be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonant to the Scriptures, is lawful: Therefore ſuch Worſhip as this may be lawfully impoſed by the Magiſtrate. To both Propoſitions I anſwer in their order. To the former,</p>
            <p n="1">1. By diſtinguiſhing, and explaining in what ſence, and how far, it is to be admitted. 1. It is not <hi>lawful</hi> for the Magiſtrate to command very many things, which may notwithſtanding be <hi>lawfully</hi> done by thoſe that are commanded. A ſingle man may lawfully marry, or marry ſuch or ſuch a mans daughter, but the Magiſtrate cannot lawfully command him to do either the one of the other. So a man may <hi>lawfully</hi> give the one half of his goods unto the poor, as <hi>Zacheus</hi> did; yet the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate cannot <hi>lawfully</hi> impoſe this upon any man. Such caſes as theſe are without number. Therefore it is but a lame conſequence: It is <hi>lawful</hi> for a man to pray, or worſhip God, by a ſet Liturgie, or ſtinted Form of Prayer: therefore it is <hi>lawful</hi> for the Magiſtrate to impoſe this upon him.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Some things, ſimply, and indefinitely conſidered, and circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances ſecluded, may be <hi>lawful,</hi> the property of the <hi>lawfulneſs</hi> whereof may be altered by circumſtances, one, or more, intervening. It is a rule approved and made uſe of by a late learned Biſhop of this Land: <hi>Quod licitum eſt mutatur ex ſuperveniente cauſâ:</hi> That which is lawful may be changed, and become unlawful, by means of ſome circumſtance coming in the way, and lighting on it. This hath been explained, and
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:103564:32"/>argued formerly. Marriage or a married life, ſimply and in it ſelf con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, is <hi>lawful</hi> for men. But if men be either <hi>Eunuchs from the womb, or made ſuch by men</hi> (as our Saviour ſpeaketh) to them it is not law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full; and other circumſtances beſides theſe, may render it <hi>unlawful</hi> unto others. Stinted Forms of Prayer, in themſelves, unto ſome men, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſome circumſtances may be lawful, yet the uſe of them, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the conſtant uſe of them, to ſome other men may be unlawful; as particularly unto thoſe, upon whom God hath poured out the Spirit of Prayer upon ſuch tearms, that by the exerciſe hereof they are inabled to glorifie God, more than themſelves (and many worthy Miniſters) are by their gifts of preaching. As though men that are impotent in their limbs, or lame, may uſe crutches for their ſupport, or relief in going. Yet it had been very ſinful for thoſe, who by the ſpecial ſavour and power of God, were, either by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> or his Apoſtles, perfectly reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red unto the uſe of theis limbs, to have either neglected, or concealed, the grace of God vouchſafed unto them in that kind, by walking upon Crutches afterwards: Yea, it had been unlawful for the Council, or any Magiſtrate, to have commanded them thus to do. So that things that are ſimply and in themſelves <hi>lawful,</hi> but unto ſome men are, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to others may, by circumſtances, become <hi>unlawful,</hi> cannor <hi>lawfully</hi> (by a general command at leaſt, and which ſhall equally, and without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, exact obedience from all men) be commanded by the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate: and conſequently, the uſe of ſet Forms of Prayer, though <hi>law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful</hi> in it ſelf, cannot <hi>lawfully</hi> be thus commanded by him.</p>
            <p n="3">3. (And laſtly, for the Propoſition in hand) Things that are meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and only <hi>lawful</hi> (or in ſuch a ſence, as things <hi>lawful,</hi> are oppoſed unto, or di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>inguiſhed from things that are <hi>expedient,</hi> as the Apoſtle himſelf oppoſeth them, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.12. <hi>and</hi> 10.23.) doubtleſs are not in whole, or in part, the object of the Magiſtrates Authority, nor can lawfully be commanded by m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n. The reaſon is, becauſe the Power and Authority of a Magiſtrate is too ſerious, ſolemn, and ſacred an Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of God, to buſie or imploy it ſelf about triſles, or impertinen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, or things of no concernment to the benefit, or good of thoſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him. The Apoſtle ſpeaking of the Magiſtrate, <hi>He is</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the Miniſter of God to thee for GOOD</hi> [that is, for thy <hi>good,</hi> or, <hi>thy wealth,</hi> as the former tranſlation had it] He hath no Deputation, or Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion from God to uſe his Authority or Power for the gratification o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s own humour, or fancy, as by trying concluſions upon thee, whether thou wilt obey him in doing ſuch or ſuch things at his command, which have no reaſonable tendency, either to his <hi>good,</hi> or thine, or any other mans. No, the tenour of his Commiſſion ingageth him to impoſe only
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:103564:33"/>ſuch things upon thee by his Authority, which have a natural and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect tendency to the benefit and welfare of the State in which thou li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt, and conſequently to thine own. He cannot <hi>lawfully,</hi> nor without the manifeſt diſhonour of the ſacred Ordinance of Magiſtracy, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand thee to pill ſtraws, or throw ſtones againſt the wind: which acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons notwithſtanding are more unqueſtionably innocent and <hi>lawful</hi> (in the ſence explained) then the uſing of thoſe <hi>indifferent</hi> things called Ceremonies, in the Worſhip of God; and of as much conducement to the Publick Good, as they. Therefore it is far beneath the ſublime Dignity of the Divine Ordinance of Magiſtracy, to intereſt it ſelf in commanding either the one, or the other.</p>
            <p n="2">2ly. The Minor Propoſition was, <hi>But the Worſhip of God performed by ſtinted Liturgies, if theſe be conſonant to the Scriptures, is lawful.</hi> This hath been alleady weighed in the Ballance, and found light: Yet to give meaſure heaped up; we repeat, and adde (together)</p>
            <p n="1">1. In that ſence of the word <hi>lawful,</hi> in which the ſame word muſt be taken in the former Propoſition to make that paſſable (as it was late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly declared and diſtinguiſhed) this Propoſition is to be denied. For the Worſhip of God here deſcribed, though it ſhould be admitted <hi>lawful</hi> in ſome ſence, or with reference to ſome perſons; yet this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth it not to be of that kind of things <hi>lawful,</hi> which the Magiſtrate hath a <hi>lawful</hi> power to command, eſpecially by a general Command, and which he intendeth ſhall obliege all men. It hath been ſhewed and proved, 1. That there are many things <hi>lawful</hi> to be <hi>performed</hi> and done by many, which the Magiſtrate cannot <hi>lawfully</hi> command them to do. And, 2. That ſome things may be <hi>lawful</hi> for ſome men to do, which are not <hi>lawful</hi> for all, and conſequently cannot <hi>lawfully</hi> be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded unto all. So that the Syllogiſm is fallacious and captious, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving four terms in it, (as <hi>Logicians</hi> ſpeak) inſtead of three, and ſo proveth nothing, unleſs (haply) the intent of the Author to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive.</p>
            <p n="2">2. A <hi>Liturgy</hi> may be <hi>conſonant to the Scriptures</hi> either in reſpect of the Matter of it, or of the Form, or in reſpect of both: Nor can it in truth be ſaid to be conſonant unto them, unleſs it accordeth with them in both. Our great <hi>Liturgy</hi>-Maſters, in their Diſcourſes upon this ſubject, and pleadings for the Service-Book, ſeem to eſtimate the <hi>conſonancy</hi> we now ſpeak of, onely by the <hi>Matter</hi> of the <hi>Liturgy,</hi> not bringing the <hi>Form</hi> to account in their reckoning this way. And (indeed) in reference to the defence of their Service-Book, they do very providentially and prudently, to take no notice of any neceſſity of ſuch or ſuch a Form in a <hi>Liturgy,</hi> to make it <hi>conſonant</hi> to the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:103564:33"/>For the greateſt part of the <hi>Matter</hi> of this Book, is juſtifiable enough by the Scriptures: and for thoſe paſſages and expreſſions which are guilty, by far-fetch'd and forc'd interpretations, and by authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tative wranglings, or ſome ſemblable phraſes, or ſayings found in ſome counterfeit or ſuſpected Antiquity, they are able to qualifie (in part) the demerit of them. But the <hi>Form</hi> of this Book, and the diſpoſition of the ſeveral parts of the matter contained in it, is ſo ſtrangely and daringly extravagant and exorbitant from all Patterns, Methods and Carriages of Prayer or Worſhip, recorded in the Scriptures, that I know not what ſalve they are able to find out for the grievous ſore of this ſo broad and monſtrous a diſſonancy of it from them. And (doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs) the Form of a <hi>Liturgy,</hi> or Prayer, is not a thing ſo inconſiderable, but that, though the matter of it be never ſo ſavoury and ſound, yea, nothing but the very words and ſayings of the Scripture it ſelf, yet may the wiſdom of the fleſh (which is fooliſhneſs with God) have ſo much to do, and ſo ill acquit it ſelf in the putting them together, that the compoſition will not be meet to be exhibited or preſented unto God. So then, if by a <hi>Liturgy conſonant unto the Scriptures,</hi> the Propoſition meaneth <hi>conſonant</hi> in <hi>Matter</hi> only, whatever the <hi>Form</hi> be, (which ſeems to be the meaning of it) it is manifeſtly untrue: <hi>A Worſhip performed by a Liturgy conſonant to the Scriptures</hi> [onely in ſuch a ſenſe] <hi>is not law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. (And laſtly, for this alſo) <hi>The Worſhip performed by a Liturgy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonant to the Scriptures</hi> may be <hi>lawful</hi> [namely if it be left free, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commanded] and yet be <hi>unlawful,</hi> if impoſed. It was <hi>lawful</hi> for the People of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to uſe an Altar made of <hi>whole Stones,</hi> to offer their Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices upon; but if any man had <hi>lift up a tool</hi> upon the ſame ſtones, the Altar made of them had been <hi>polluted, (Exod.</hi> 20.25. <hi>Deut.</hi> 27.5. <hi>Joſh.</hi> 8.31.) A lawful Worſhip, or Form of Worſhip, by the lifting up of an authoritative Command upon it by Men, becomes hereby <hi>unlawful,</hi> [eſpecially if <hi>performed</hi> upon the account, or by vertue of this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, as hath been formerly ſignified] becauſe in ſuch a caſe the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture commanding, hath Divine Honour done unto it, and is admitted as an Umpire, and as having Authority over the things of God. For what can we imagine ſhould be the <hi>things of God,</hi> as contra-diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by our Saviour himſelf, unto the <hi>things of Caeſar,</hi> if matters apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining to his Worſhip, and the diſpoſal nereof, be none of thoſe things, but muſt be inventoried amongſt <hi>Caeſars</hi> goods alſo? He that ſhall give unto <hi>Caeſar</hi> the things which are Gods, and ſo diſmember and cut ſho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t his Patrimony in the World, it is much to be feared that he will ſend him unto <hi>Ceſar</hi> for his Reward. But of theſe things at large already.
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:103564:34"/>We ſee by what hath been argued upon both Propoſitions, that in the whole Argument there is little but fraud and confuſion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Some there are who count it a ſmall thing to contend for the lawfulneſs onely of impoſing Liturgies and Forms of Prayer; they run for a higher prize, attempting to evince and prove that there is a ſingular expediency, and ſo a kind of neceſſity of ſuch Impoſitions. The Argument by which they hope to effect this great thing, ſheweth it ſelf in theſe or the like Colours.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>That which is a proper and effectual means to prevent many great and ſad inconveniences, and dangerous eruptions of ſpirit, whereinto Miniſters, being left at liberty in their praying publickly, are apt to fall; is very expedient and neceſſary to be done.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But the impoſition of limited and ſet Forms of Prayer by the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, is a proper and effectual means for ſuch a purpoſe.</hi> Ergo.</p>
            </q>
            <p>By the <hi>ſad inconveniences and dangerous eruptions of ſpirit,</hi> &amp;c. (here mentioned) the Argumentators mean confuſedneſs of method, tauto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logies, or needleſs reiterations of the ſame things, broken ſentences, and ill-accommodated with ſenſe (with ſuch-like) on the one hand: and on the other, Complaints unto God againſt Truths, under the name of Errours; ventings of diſ-affection to the preſent Government or Governours; Petitions and paſſages ſavouring of Sedition, Treaſon, Rebellion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> All theſe, and the like (ſay theſe men) may be effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually prevented by a ſtrict confinement of Miniſters unto ſuch Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Forms of Praying which are ſound and wholeſome, and free from all ſuch ſtrains of ſcandal and offence. This reaſon is, all that it is, in face; the heart of it is hollow and empty. For,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Let the Promoters of it tell us whether they approve of this ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guing or no (which we ſhall immediately ſubjoyn) or whether it be not parallel unto theirs.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>That which is a proper and effectual means to prevent the ſins of adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, fornication, inceſt, theft, murther, ſedition, treaſon, rebellion,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>into which men are apt to fall, cannot but be judged expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent and neceſſary to be put in execution.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But for the Magiſtrate to put all men capable of theſe ſins into ſtrong Priſons, and there to keep them cloſe in Chains and Fetters of Iron, all the days of their lives, Is a proper and effectual means to prevent the perpetration of theſe Sins.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:103564:34"/>
               <p>Ergo, <hi>This courſe is expedient and neceſſary to be taken and put in execution.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>There is no reaſonable ground of exception againſt the parallel or compariſon: For the means ſpecified in the latter Argument is every whit as proper and <hi>effectual</hi> (nay, of the two, both the more proper and more effectual, as might be ſhewed, if need were) for the end and purpoſe here mentioned, as the means pretended in the other, for the end commended there. Wherefore if it be a courſe moſt importune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ſenceleſly injurious and tyrannical, to keep men in Priſon and Chains as long as they live, to prevent their miſcarryings in the high miſdemeanours mentioned, or the like, before they have offended in any of them: It cannot reaſonably but be judged very prepoſterous, and moſt unworthy men of Reaſon and Conſcience, to confine the Spirit of Prayer in the moſt worthy Miniſters and Servants of God, (in whom (poſſibly) he delights to ſhew himſelf in much of his glory) within the limits and bars of ſtinted Forms of Prayer, and theſe of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane contrivance, onely for fear leſt this Spirit failing them, they ſhould fall to pray by an unclean ſpirit; and pray either their igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, or diſtemper'd paſſions, ſedition, treaſon, or the like. Penal ſufferings may and ought (indeed) to be inflicted for the prevention of Sin; but onely upon thoſe that have ſinned, not upon the Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent.</p>
            <p>If it be replied, That to be commanded by the Magiſtrate to uſe a ſet Form of Prayer, is not penal unto any man: I anſwer, 1. That as the unclean converſation of the men of <hi>Sodom</hi> was vexatious to the <hi>righteous Soul of Lot;</hi> ſo muſt needs the Commands of Authority, which are <hi>ſpiritually</hi> unclean, and provoking to defile the Marriage-Bed wherein God vouchſafe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h the enjoyment of himſelf as a Spiritual Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band (I mean his Worſhip; for ſo the Scripture reſembleth it frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.16. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57.7, 8. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 23.17, 41. and in all thoſe places, which are many, where Idolatrous and falſe Worſhip are metaphori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally expreſſed under the terms of Whoredom, Adultery, Fornication, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) ſuch Commands (I ſay) muſt needs be much more afflicting and ſadding to the Spirits and Souls of Conſcientious and holy Men, when they cannot conceive or apprehend them but as ſuch, [I mean as ſpiritually unclean, and tempting unto folly with a ſtrange God.] 2. To him that cannot, with the good leave of his Conſcience, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to ſuch a Command, which is impoſed on him with a penalty, it is (conſtructively) the ſame, to have the penalty inflicted on him with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Command given, and to have the Command impoſed on him upon ſuch terms.</p>
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:103564:35"/>
            <p n="2">2. To the Argument under debate, I anſwer further, That to impoſe a <hi>Form</hi> of Prayer, is no <hi>effectual or proper means</hi> to prevent any of the evils mentioned, unleſs a <hi>Form</hi> of Preaching be impoſed alſo. For they that are apt to tranſgreſs in any of the miſcarriages ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified, are as likely to do it in Preaching as in Praying; and have no leſs opportunity (if not a greater) for the doing it, in the former than in the latter. And if all, both Preachings and Prayings, ſhall be reduced unto <hi>Forms,</hi> the <hi>ABCdarian</hi> Schools may ſend forth Boys as well accompliſhed for the publick work of the Miniſtry as the <hi>Acade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mian</hi>-men.</p>
            <p n="3">3. If the Impoſitions contended for, were in any degree <hi>proper,</hi> and <hi>neceſſary</hi> to prevent the ſins mentioned, it is more ſtrange than to be believed, that the Lord <hi>Chriſt,</hi> who was as <hi>faithful unto God in all his houſe, as was Moſes, Heb.</hi> 3.2. and withal, as great an enemy to the miſdemeanours expreſſed in the Argument, as the moſt zealouſly-de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout <hi>Formaliſt</hi> can be, ſhould notwithſtanding, neither by himſelf, nor any of his Apoſtles, ſpeak the leaſt word of any ſuch thing; eſpecially, having by the greateſt of theſe given men warning <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>not to preſume</hi> (as the former tranſlation rendred it) or, not to be wiſe, above that which is written (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.6.) yea and by himſelf (as was propheſied of him, <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.24.) <hi>ſealed up the Viſion and Propheſie,</hi> Rev. 22.18. and ſo left no place for Humane Wiſdom to interpoſe for the introducing any more Laws or Conſtitutions, for the Government or Advancement of his Kingdom, than thoſe, which he hath left us expreſly, and in ſo many words, in the New Teſtament, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with ſuch, which are vertually, and truly included, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in theſe, not ſuch, which either by forc't, or far-fetch't, or by ſubtile and gloſſie conſequences, derive their Authority from them.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Men that are in any degree meet to be admitted unto the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice and Work of the Miniſtry, are not ſo apt, or prone, to fall into any of the foul miſcarriages feared in the Argument, or ſo like <hi>unto the Horſe or Mule, that have no underſtanding,</hi> that their <hi>mouths</hi> need be <hi>held in with the bit and bridle</hi> of impoſed Forms of Prayer, <hi>leſt they come too near</hi> unto them that are afraid to be touched, or behave themſelves ſo extravagantly and unchriſtianly in that ſacred part of their function, as is ſuggeſted againſt them that they are like to do. If they be of the houſhold of Faith, in caſe they <hi>know not what they ſhould pray for as they ought, the Spirit [of God] helpeth their infirmities,</hi> Rom. 8.26. But they that Impoſe Forms, take this work out of the hand of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> and <hi>help</hi> mens <hi>infirmities</hi> themſelves, inabling and directing them by
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:103564:35"/>Book, <hi>what they ſhould pray for as they ought.</hi> I am far from ſuppoſing the ſin of impoſing Forms, to be that ſin againſt the Spirit, by which men are ſealed to the vengeance of eternal fire: but am very near believing, that it is an high affront and indignity offered unto him. For, whereas it is his moſt glorious intereſt, 1. To raiſe what variety of ſpiritual and heavenly ſtrains of Devotion he pleaſeth, in the hearts and minds of his Miniſters, whilſt they are miniſtring in the Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies of his Saints: And, 2. To give them what ſweetneſs of Lip, what pleaſantneſs of Utterance he pleaſeth (as being the Lord of all Language and ſpeech) for the communicatnig of thoſe bleſſed im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions and conceptions, unto the People before them, to the beſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage for their edification and comfort; they who confine theſe Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters unto their Forms of Prayer, ſay (in effect) unto the <hi>Spirit,</hi> Thy Miniſters, in their publick ſervice, ſhall be at our allowance, and not thine, both for the ſtrains of their inward Devotion, and for the Language and Words, wherein they ſhall utter them unto the People. Thou either wilt not, or canſt not, order them regularly, and accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to our mindes, and as we think meet, in their prayings; at leaſt, we can have no aſſurance of thee that thou wilt do it. Therefore we judge it better, and more ſafe for us to thruſt ſuch words into their mouths, and ſo to neceſſitate and force ſuch diſpoſitions and deſires within them (unleſs their tongues go one way, and their hearts and thoughts another way, at the ſame time) which we are ſure are inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent and good, then to leave them to thy guidance and aſſiſtance (whereof we are ſo uncertain) although thy purpoſe and intent may be to glorifie thy ſelf at a far better rate, in them and by them, as in the manifoldneſs of thy Wiſdom, and excellenty of thy Power, the riches of thy Grace and Bounty towards thy People, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in caſe we ſhould leave them free unto thee. Whether ſuch a greeting as this be not high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reproachful to the ever-bleſſed Spirit of Grace, and not far (if any thing) ſhort of Blaſphemy? and whether mens impoſitions of Forms of Prayer (being duly and without any ſtraining, or wreſting, inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted) do not ſpeak all this, yea and more in the ſame kind unto him, I refer to the conſciences of theſe men themſelves, when they ſhall be thoroughly awakned, to judge. In the mean time, if care were taken cloſely to purſue the Apoſtle <hi>Paul's</hi> orders about the Miniſterial Function, ſo as to lay hands upon none, but ſuch as are <hi>Sober, Watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, Juſt, Holy, Temperate, Lovers of good things, Apt</hi> (or Able) <hi>to Teach, not Self-will'd, not ſoon Angry,</hi> &amp;c. They need not be taught, as we uſe to teach Children, and defectives in underſtanding, how to ſpeak, nor yet be feared, or ſuſpected, as perſons likely to break out in
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:103564:36"/>any of thoſe dangerous and enormous miſcarriages of themſelves, which the Argument pretendeth. Or if thoſe that are created Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, be but <hi>Epiſcopally</hi> given, and true-born Sons of the Church (as ſome love to ſpeak) even Birds of this Feather are not ſo unnatural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly evil, as to defile their own neſt, or to blaſpheme either the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or Governours, that are ſo propitious and indulgent unto them. Therefore,</p>
            <p n="5">5. (And laſtly, for this) There are pregnant grounds of ſuſpition, that the invention and device of the firſt Impoſer of Lyturgies, and Forms of Prayer, are not ſo highly praiſed, or ſo hotly proſecuted, by their Poſterity in theſe dayes (eſpecially amongſt us) for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention of the evils ſuggeſted in the Argument, but rather for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moting of other evils, or prevention of ſome Good things, becauſe they ſeem evil unto ſome. It is a frequent policy, which this Verſe expreſſeth:
<q>
                  <hi>Ut verae lateant cauſae, finguntur inanes.</hi>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <l>Falſe grounds for actings ſometimes are pretended,</l>
                  <l>To hide from ſight thoſe really intended.</l>
               </q> 
               <hi>Tautologies,</hi> needleſs repetitions, broken ſentences, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived Prayers of Miniſters, are no real grief of heart to our Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſers: the Liturgie which they impoſe, and which giveth pleaſures to their ſoul from the one end of it unto the other, is full of theſe Warts on the Face of it (as we have ſeen formerly) nor are their conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſo ſtrait and narrow, but that they can ſwallow Gnats of a larger kind than theſe. And thoſe things, which in the prayers of Godly and conſcientious Miniſters they deſire, and intend to prevent, under the hateful names of <hi>venting diſordered paſſions, diſcontents againſt their Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d Government, Petitions and paſsages ſavouring of Sedition, Treaſon,</hi> &amp;c. are the <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> zealous, and faithful deportments of ſuch Miniſters, in confeſſing before God the ſins of their Kings, Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and Governours, in reproving them, and denouncing the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God againſt them, unleſs they repent: in admoniſhing and warning the People committed unto them, that they be not enſnared to deſtruction, by following their evil examples, or complying with them in things diſpleaſing unto God, in praying for them, when they walk in wayes that are not good, that God will pleaſe to forgive them and turn their hearts unto his Teſtimonies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Inſtead of theſe, and ſuch like worthy and faithful dealings with their Rulers and Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:103564:36"/>according to the example of the true Prophets of God, and other godly perſons of old (as they are recorded in the Scripture) the Forms of praying for them, which are now impoſed on Miniſters, are flat and flattering, no ways agreeable or proper to their ſtates or conditions, if they be not perſons truly fearing God: which the World too well knows not to be the caſe and condition of all that bear Rule in it. Yea, in ſome of theſe Forms of Prayer, whereof we now particularly ſpeak, ſuch perſons are recommended unto God, which are not ſo much as in being: and in others of them (indeed in moſt of them, if not in all) ſuch things are deſired of God for them, which, if granted, are more like to turn to a ſnare, or curſe unto many of them, than to a bleſſing indeed. They are more (generally) o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a very erroneous and much miſtaken calculation, for the real good of many of them.</p>
            <p>With what other motives, and carnal projections our high Clergie Men (for theſe are the Maſters of the Mint of all our impoſed Forms, with their reſpective Impoſitions) are enthuſiaſed into their fiery zeal to have the Conſciences of the free People of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> both Miniſters and People, yoked with the iron yokes of Lyturgies, and ſtinted Forms of Devotion, I ſhall not now enquire. They claim the higheſt prehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minence of Office in the Church of <hi>Chriſt:</hi> and there being little or nothing for them here to do, as ſuch by Chriſt's aſſignment (as was formerly hinted) they were tempted by the grandure of their uſurped Office, to caſt about for ſome imployment anſwerable hereunto, leſt their nakedneſs ſhould be ſeen by men, and they bear the reproach of being <hi>Clouds without water.</hi> How prudently and appoſitely to their purpoſe, they have pitched upon the ordering and exerciſing the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian</hi> World (as far as they have to do in it) with impoſed Lyturgies, and Forms of Prayers, would make too long a ſtory to be told here: it may be related elſe-where at one time or other.</p>
            <p>Several other pretences are inſiſted on to entitle men to a joynt right of Power with God, for the appointment of his Worſhip by Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgies eſpecially, and limited Devotions, (for the Procurators of this Cauſe are ſo deep in love with it, that unleſs they carry it, they dye) which are ſo empty and weak, that to enter into a conteſt with them, would be to make more of them than they are. <hi>Recitaſſe, refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſſe eſt.</hi> For they plead, 1. That a Liberty left unto Miniſters to uſe publickly their acquired faculty of Praying, or of <hi>talking boldly unto God before People</hi> (as our <hi>Grand Debater,</hi> prophanely enough, praſeth t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> For to acknowledge a <hi>gift</hi> of Prayer in any man, is unto theſe men as the ſhadow of Death) is but fuel to feed the evil h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mour; of pride,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:103564:37"/>vain-glory, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> therefore it is better denied then granted unto them. But would they, who thus argue, be content, upon the credit of their Argument, to be denied the poſſeſſion and enjoyment of their great places of Power and Domination in the Church, or of their luxuriant Revenues? For (doubtleſs) theſe are a kind of fewel more apt and dangerous to feed the fire of Pride, Ambition, Lordlineſs and Cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, in them. Or do they think it better for them, that God, by ſome ſtroke of Sickneſs, or the like, ſhould deprive them of their Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, Wits, Underſtandings, Learning, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> becauſe they may make fewel of them, to feed and nouriſh the ſinful humours of Pride, and Vain-glory, then that he ſhould grant unto them the <hi>liberty</hi> of uſing and enjoying them? The notion of Truth in this Verſe, is too hard for the Argument:
<q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Nil prodeſt, quod non laedere poſſit idem.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>There is no profitable thing,</l>
                     <l>But what may hurt and damage bring.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The lovelineſs of Uniformity and Conſent amongſt Miniſters united under the ſame Civil Government, raviſheth the Judgments of ſome into an high approbation of Liturgies and Forms of Prayer impoſed. But may not Miniſters be uniform and conſenting in Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, unleſs they all preach, and this conſtantly, one and the ſame Sermon <hi>verbatim?</hi> Or would it argue that the Metropolitan and his Dioceſan were at odds, [if in caſe THEY ſhould happen to preach] the one ſhould take his Text out of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> the other out of St. <hi>Peter? Apagè quiſquilias!</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Our <hi>Grand Debater</hi> tells us ſad Stories of men, whoſe names, for their moſt admired and rare faculties in extemporary Praying, might have been <hi>None-ſuch;</hi> and who for their horrid and unparallel'd wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs and blaſphemies likewiſe need not have changed this name. Of both theſe characters, compaſſing the Earth to and fro, he findes three men; in <hi>Germany,</hi> one <hi>Swenckfield,</hi> (a notorious <hi>Arch-Heretick</hi>) in <hi>England,</hi> one <hi>Hacket,</hi> a Blaſphemer; in <hi>Muſcovia, John Baſilides,</hi> (Duke of this Country) who (it ſeems) was <hi>an horrid Hell-Hound.</hi> For theſe wicked mens ſakes <hi>conceived Prayer</hi> muſt be caſt out of the Church as a menſtruous Cloth, and Liturgies and Forms of Prayer impoſed, like fine pure white ſhining Linen, brought into the Church in its ſtead. <hi>Similes habeat labra lactucas.</hi> Like Cauſe, like Plea. A carnal Intereſt (I ſee) is as bad as a Gift, which (as the Scripture
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:103564:37"/>ſaith) <hi>blindeth the Eyes of the Wiſe:</hi> Otherwiſe a man of his Parts and Learning would never have leaned on ſuch a broken Reed as this, which pierceth his own hand. For is not this reaſoning of the ſame calculation, or rather of a far better? Biſhop <hi>John</hi> the thirteenth was a man monſtrouſly vicious, guilty of the foul crimes of Inceſt, Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Perjury, Extortion, and what not? Biſhop <hi>Silveſter</hi> the ſecond, was a Sorcerer, and compacted with the Devil for his Biſhoprick. Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop <hi>Hildebrand</hi> was a moſt wicked and reprobate Monſter, a Necro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mancer, a Conjurer, a Murtherer, a man of whoſe villanies Hiſtories are aſhamed: All theſe were Biſhops of one and the ſame See, and this called <hi>Apoſtolical:</hi> And beſides theſe three, there have been ſeven times three more, Biſhops alſo of the ſame See, equal unto theſe in ways and practices of all kinds, hateful and abominable in the ſight of God and men: And how many others of the Epiſcopal Inveſtiture in other parts of the World, have been <hi>evil Beaſts, idle Bellies,</hi> Peſts and Vipers, where they have had to do, who is able to conceive or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend? Therefore down with the <hi>Hierarchy,</hi> down with it even to the ground, and let the place of it in the Church know it no more, but let Paſtors and Teachers govern the Churches of Chriſt in its ſtead. Will the Gentleman acknowledge any concluding force in ſuch an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument as this? Yet evident it is, that it hath ten times more ſtrength in it, for the removal of Epiſcopacy out of the Church, then his rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning hath againſt conceived Prayer. Becauſe <hi>Satan</hi> ſometimes <hi>transformeth himſelf into an Angel of Light;</hi> is it any reaſon why an Angel of Light indeed, ſhould, if it were poſſible, transform himſelf into ſome dark and dull Creature? But (doubtleſs) ſuch Arguments as theſe will never bring Liturgies into, nor conceived Prayers out of, requeſt.</p>
            <p>Yet there is one Argument more, wherewith the Friends of Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy-Devotion impoſed, pleaſe themſelves not a little in their way. This we ſhall take into a little conſideration, and herewith conclude. The Plea is this: That not the uſe onely, but the impoſition alſo of Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies and Forms of Prayer, however now quarelled by ſome amongſt us, have been allowed and practiſed in the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Church ancient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; yea, and are at this day admitted and practiſed in many, if not in all the Reformed Churches abroad. I ſhall not enlarge the diſcourſe, either with an examination of the truth of what is here affirmed, or in weighing the validity or pertinency of the pretences, in caſe they ſhould be found Realities and Truths, otherwiſe then as I find them ready weighed to my hand in the Ballance of the Sanctuary. Onely theſe two things by the way: 1. That I do not believe the impoſition
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:103564:38"/>of Liturgies to be ſo ancient amongſt <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> as ſeems to be ſuggeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Plea. 2. That I know that the Liturgies (if they muſt be ſo called) which are uſed in other Reformed Churches, taſte much more ſavourly of the Reformation, then that impoſed upon us.</p>
            <p>When our Saviour propheſieth thus, <hi>Every Plant which my heavenly Father hath not planted,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ſhall be plucked up by the Roots,</hi> (Mat. 15.13.) he clearly ſupporeth that Practices and Opinions in the Church, which are not pleaſing unto God, becauſe not of his <hi>planting,</hi> may not onely ſpring up, and get in hither, and find place here, but a ſo take rooting, [that is, may work and wind into, and (as it were) wrap themſelves about the Judgements and Conſciences, yea, and inſinuate into the affections al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o, not onely of multitudes of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon or meaner ſort of men, but even of many pious, learned, and great men likewiſe; for without this, they could never take ſuch deep and faſt <hi>rooting,</hi> as is here intimated they may.] Now this rooting of the Plants we ſpeak of, in the Church, ſuppoſeth a poſſibility, or rather a probability of their long continuance here, before they come to be plucked up by the Roots. Plants that have thruſt their Roo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s well in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Earth, and have ſpread and wrapt them about the Clods and Stones thereof, are like to grow, and flouriſh, and bring forth Fruit for many years. The Metaphor, by which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he abolition and caſting out of theſe <hi>Apocryphal</hi> Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ces, and D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ctrines, from the Church, is here expreſſed, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſhall being e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, pull'd, or (rather) <hi>torn up by the Roots;</hi> implieth, that when God will endure them no longer, but ſet his Labourers and Servants on work effectually to oppoſe them, in order to their utter and final aboliſhment, the ſervice may prove ſomewhat hot, and that the Perſons ſtrongly devoted to them, are like to ſwell, and rage, and fume, and to endeavour to raiſe a great duſt both amongſt great and ſmall, to turn every ſtone; yea, and <hi>Acheronta mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere,</hi> to <hi>dig into Hell,</hi> (as the Prophet <hi>Amos</hi> ſpeaketh, Chap. 9.2.) to ſave their darling Inventions, their old Idol-Practices and Doctrines, if it were poſſible, from the hand of Heaven, which is now ſtretched out againſt them. Even as a Tree that hath been a long time grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in a Soyl proper for it, and where it hath thriven amain, ſo that with the numerous Roots of it, it hath taken ſtrong and faſt hold on the Earth round about it, far and near; in caſe it ſhould be forced, or turn'd up by the Roots, either by a Tempeſt, or ſtrong guſt of Wind, or by ſome Engi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e deviſed for ſuch a purpoſe, or the like, it would tear up the Earth on every ſide of it, and raiſe and bring up with it Stones, and Gravel, and Dirt, and whatſoever it could take hold on, to ſecure it againſt the force that now attempteth the extirpation and downfal of it.</p>
            <pb n="67" facs="tcp:103564:38"/>
            <p>Again, That <hi>Hay, Wood, and Stubble</hi> in ſpiritual and Church-Build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, may for a long time be in equal eſteem with, and paſs (more ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally) for <hi>Silver, Gold, and precious Stones;</hi> and yet in proceſs of time (it may be not till after many Ages) be detected to be but a baſe kind of material, very improper for ſuch a building; and ſo come to be pull'd out of it, and thrown away; the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> emphatically de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clareth, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.12, 13. in theſe words: <hi>Now if any man build upon this Foundation, Gold, Silver, precious Stones, Wood, Hay, Stubble, eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry mans Work ſhall be made manifeſt. For the day</hi> [that is, ſaith <hi>Grotius,</hi> with other Interpreters, <hi>longum tempus,</hi> length of time] <hi>ſhall declare it: becauſe it ſhall be</hi> [or is to be] <hi>revealed by fire,</hi> &amp;c. Meaning, 1. That Time, in the duration, progreſs, and continuance of it, will be ſound as ſevere and ſearching an Examiner or Trier of mens Church-work in every kind, as Fire is of Metals. 2. That there are, or may be, ſome bad Materials made uſe of in Church. Work, the badneſs where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of will not (in reaſon cannot, or is not like to) be diſcovered or made <hi>manifeſt,</hi> until they have paſſed the teſt and trial of many Generations. So then, the long continuance, whether of the free uſe onely, (which is the more tolerable) of Liturgies, and ſtinted Prayers in the Church of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> or of the Impoſition of them, (which is the more unchriſtian and inſupportable) is an Argument of no intereſt or weight at all, to juſtifie or prove, either the lawfulneſs, much leſs the expediency, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the one, or of the other. I end with the ſaying of <hi>Tertullian: Veritati poteſt nemo praeſcribere, non ſpacium temporum, non patrocinia per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonarum:</hi> that is, There is no preſcription [or Plea] neither of any length of time, nor of the patrocinations [or Authoritative Aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the contrary] of any Perſons whatſoever, that is of any force or value againſt the Truth.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="68" facs="tcp:103564:39"/>
            <head>Poſtſcript.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>NOn attendamus quid ante nos aliquis fecerit, ſed qui ante omnes eſt, Chriſtus prior fecerit.</hi> Cypr.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sapientiam ſibi adimunt, qui ſine ullo judicio inventa majorum probant, &amp; ab aliis pecudum more, ducuntur.</hi> Lactant.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Magnos Errores magnorum virorum Authoritate perſuaſi, tranſmittimus.</hi> Vadianus.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cautum debet reddere, non ſequacem, Error alienus.</hi> Ra. Ardens.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Honeſtiſsimum, majorum veſtigia ſequi, ſi recto itinere praeceſſerint.</hi> Plin. Ep. 8.5.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mala Pax eſt, &amp; Concordia, quae inter Paſtores &amp; Lupos eſt.</hi> Chemnit. Harm.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Maledicta ſit Charitas, &amp; Concordia, propter quam conſervandam periclitari neceſſe ſit Verbum Dei.</hi> Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>in</hi> Gal. 5.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pios hoc nomen &amp; titulum in mundo oportet gerere, quod
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:103564:39"/>Seditioſi, ac Schiſmatici, ac infinitorum malorum Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res ſunt.</hi> Idem ibidem.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Heu, heu, Domine! ipſi ſunt in perſecutione tua primi, qui in Eccleſia tua videntur principatum diligere, &amp; gerere principatum.</hi> Bern. de Conver. S. Pauli, Serm. 1.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ignoſci potuit ſimpliciter errantibus: poſt inspirationem vero, &amp; revelationem factam, ſine ignorantiae venia pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catur.</hi> Cypr. Ep. 63.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qui vero me errare existimant, etiam atque etiam dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genter, quae ſunt dicta, conſiderent, ne ſortaſsis ipſi errent.</hi> Auguſt. De Bono Perſever.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Theſe Sayings may be Engliſhed as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let us not regard or minde what ſome have done before us, but what <hi>Chriſt,</hi> who is before all, hath firſt done.</p>
            <p>They take a courſe never to attain unto wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, who, without Judgement, approve of the Inventions of their Fore-Fathers; and like unto Sheep, are led by others.</p>
            <p>Sometimes we let paſs great Errors [as if they were Truths] being perſwaded [hereunto] by the Authority of Great Men.</p>
            <pb n="70" facs="tcp:103564:40"/>
            <p>The Errors of others ſhould not move us to follow, but to look about us.</p>
            <p>It is moſt honeſt [and honourable] to follow the ſteps of our Fore-Fathers, if they have gone before in a Right Way.</p>
            <p>It is no good Peace or Agreement that is made between Shepherds and Wolves.</p>
            <p>Accurſed be that Charity and Accord, for the conſervation [and maintenance] whereof, the Word of God muſt be endangered.</p>
            <p>Godly [and good] men muſt be content in the World to bear the name and title of being Sedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, Schiſmatical, and the Authors of a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Miſchiefs.</p>
            <p>Alas, Lord, alas! they are the prime men in perſecuting thee, who are ſeen to affect Primacy in thy Church, and to bear Rule there.</p>
            <p>God might pardon them, whilſt they ſimply [and for want of Knowledge] went aſtray: but when they have received the Truth by Inſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Revelation, they ſin without any allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of Favour for their Ignorance.</p>
            <p>They who think I am in an Error, let them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain and again diligently conſider what hath been ſaid, leſt (haply) themſelves prove to be the Men that err.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:103564:40"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
